<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-05T11:47:01+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Queer Tools</title><subtitle>Notes Toward a Dissertation</subtitle><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><entry><title type="html">Sex and Flesh</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/flesh/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sex and Flesh" /><published>2022-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/flesh</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/flesh/">&lt;p&gt;Since the spring my ideas for this chapter have solidified, and I am
beginning to see what the argument may look like. In the past few days
the fragments are coming together as a whole, to my surprise, as I’ve
become increasingly desperate, beating my head against a wall to make
two things talk to each other which don’t speak the same language –
media archaeology and black feminist studies. In looking for some way
to talk about race and technology from a material standpoint, I landed
on the concept of the flesh, and have been struggling to theorize from
black feminist notions of flesh (beginning with Spillers through
Snorton and Musser) to get at this kind of radical potential contained
within the flesh, which operates through opacity and surface. In my
reading of Black Femininist thinking on the flesh, particularly
Snorton, what I found was a capacious way of thinking about the
intersection of two registers, of the material (flesh) and
cultural/symbolic (race/gender), which I can apply back to my thinking
about technology, and the intersecting registers of the digital and
analog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But more on this later. For now, I want to highlight two things:
first, how relieved I am and ridiculous I feel to realize that one of
the texts that I analyze in this chapter, &lt;em&gt;Dawn&lt;/em&gt; by Octavia Butler,
&lt;em&gt;is in fact&lt;/em&gt; queer, because of the alien sex which uses a nonbinary
intermediary (duh!). I wanted to write about the alien sex (which is
why I chose this text) but had always approached it as a straight kind
of sex in my head, because of the male and female “terminals”, so to
speak. However, now I do feel compelled to address the whole question
of what “counts” as queer, and whether it should be independent of
sex/gender, especially considering race and the conversations occuring
in black feminist studies around this question, which I think is
really the future of queer studies. Something else to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second thing will require more time and space to think about. How
do I talk about the flesh, mobilize ideas of the flesh, without
feeling like I’m instrumentalizing it? I’m trying to think with the
flesh, in looking at what it opens up, but cannot help feeling that my
work continues some kind of exploitation, which I don’t want to be a
part of. I think the solution is to continually consider my
positionality as I do the project, and to be explicit about it in my
writing and teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a summary of the chapter as I am envisioning it now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This chapter looks at the materiality of digital media by harnessing
concepts of the flesh as developed in black feminsist studies. First I
consider how the flesh has been theorized in black feminist studies,
particularly C. Riley Snorton’s theorization of the “transcapable,”
which offers an analytic for understanding the kind of capacious
thinking required when two registers combine—the physical/analog and
the immaterial/digital. Throughout this converstation, I incorporate a
discussion of Octavia Butler’s novel, &lt;em&gt;Dawn&lt;/em&gt; (1987), as a way of
reading the intersection between the digital and analog, particularly
in the way that sexual relations occur through direct neural
stimulation between alien/human “triples,” facilitated through the
third partner, non-binary intermediary being with the ability to
connect directly to the brain’s pleasure centers. Then, I examine a
hypertext fiction work, a digital series by Entropy8Zuper! entitled
/skinonskinonskin/ (1999), and efforts at its preservation amid the
obsolescence of one of its major components, Flash technology. I trace
the complicated stack of hardware and software that facilitate the
display and preservation of this work, examining various technologies
that work in tandem such as internet networks, hypertext, and
Flash. These technologies together enable me to explore how
/skinonskinonskin/’s interface engages the intersection between the
digital and analog registers undergirding its components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><category term="Black Feminisms" /><category term="media archeology" /><category term="Octavia Butler" /><category term="hypertext" /><summary type="html">Since the spring my ideas for this chapter have solidified, and I am beginning to see what the argument may look like. In the past few days the fragments are coming together as a whole, to my surprise, as I’ve become increasingly desperate, beating my head against a wall to make two things talk to each other which don’t speak the same language – media archaeology and black feminist studies. In looking for some way to talk about race and technology from a material standpoint, I landed on the concept of the flesh, and have been struggling to theorize from black feminist notions of flesh (beginning with Spillers through Snorton and Musser) to get at this kind of radical potential contained within the flesh, which operates through opacity and surface. In my reading of Black Femininist thinking on the flesh, particularly Snorton, what I found was a capacious way of thinking about the intersection of two registers, of the material (flesh) and cultural/symbolic (race/gender), which I can apply back to my thinking about technology, and the intersecting registers of the digital and analog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Envisioning Chapter Three</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/envisioning-chap-three/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Envisioning Chapter Three" /><published>2022-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/envisioning-chap-three</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/envisioning-chap-three/">&lt;p&gt;These are some speculations for my third chapter, which I’m going to
begin researching this spring. Whereas the first two chapters were
about text analysis and text encoding, this chapter will be about
&lt;em&gt;media&lt;/em&gt;. I’m looking to explore how an attention to the material
specificity of media enhances our reading of eletronic literary work,
such as hypertext and interactive fiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theoretical focus on this paper will engage New Materialisms and
Black Feminist studies. Here, I’ll be drawing from my class last
semester with Amber Musser, where we read so many fascinating accounts
about materiality being lively, animated, vital, and about humanity
being imbricated with it. I’m thinking of authors like Jayna Brown and
Zakiyyah Iman Jackson, who work with (or work around) traditionally
white male dominated discourses about materiality and liberal humanism
to offer black female lineages of this kind of thinking. I’m also
interested in Musser’s work, whose discussion of sensuality and
fleshiness will be key for my reading of media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technological focus of this paper will be on early computer
equipment. The reason that I’m interested in older versus newer
computers is I’m interested in what Katherine N. Hayles calls
“distributed cognitive environments,” that is, the perceptual
engagement between user and computer. I think it will be easier to
study this from a historical remove, and I am also interested in the
continuous updating of technologies which forces data to shift from
one structure to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I am heavily indebted to Matt Kirschenbaum’s work in his book
&lt;em&gt;Mechanisms&lt;/em&gt; (2008), his “media archeological” method of examining the
material specificities of what is commmonly thought of “immaterial”
computing processes. I’m thinking particularly of his chapter on hard
drives. My plan is to visit a few archives (ideally the Maryland
Institute of Technology, where Kirschenbaum is based, the Media
Archeology Lab in Boulder, and the Computer History Museum in
California) to look at old hardware and software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last step is to find a literary text for all of this. I’ve been
writing about hypertext fiction (and obsolesence of Flash software)
which is one option. Probably will stick with this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><category term="media archeology" /><category term="New Materialisms" /><category term="Black Feminisms" /><summary type="html">These are some speculations for my third chapter, which I’m going to begin researching this spring. Whereas the first two chapters were about text analysis and text encoding, this chapter will be about media. I’m looking to explore how an attention to the material specificity of media enhances our reading of eletronic literary work, such as hypertext and interactive fiction.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TEI and Queer Form</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/TEI-queer-form/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TEI and Queer Form" /><published>2022-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/TEI-queer-form</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/TEI-queer-form/">&lt;p&gt;The work on chapter two has been taking longer than I thought-
there were three weeks of heavy revision in October/November, where I
made the following changes at the request of my peer reviewers. Then
a round of copyediting, which is done, and the final round of
proofreading, to be completed next week, after which the thing will
finally go to press. The major revisions included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clarifiying and foregrounding the central arguments w/r/t/ “queer
encoding” and “queer form”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expanding sections on TEI, particularly discussion on my
customization and the limitations of the tool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expanding engagement with Queer DH and Queer Historiography
scholarship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut down the overly descriptive sections on the history of the
Manuscript&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standardizing the writing style and in-text citations (to Harvard
style)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Including links to online images of the manuscript, rather than
images I took with my phone, as the Morgan did not let me use my
images for free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was doing this work, I was also preparing fellowship and grant
applicaitons. I applied for the ACLA, Ford, and Graduate Center
Dissertation Fellowships. I also applied for two research grants (was
awarded one of them so far) and to a postdoctoral position at the New
School. This is to say, I’ve been spending a lot of time theorizing my
project across cover letters, proposals, abstracts, and research,
personal, and teaching statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that I’ve been carefully theorizing is the importance of
&lt;em&gt;form&lt;/em&gt; as a connection between the queer and digital—specifically
looking at how queerness takes certain forms in literary narrative and
voice, on the one hand, and how textual data takes certain forms when
it is digitized and/or computed. To explore queer form, I’ve been
marshalling Kadji Amin, Amber Musser, and Roy Perez’s definition of
the term. They discuss queer form as a strategy for avoiding
compulsory visibility:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For our purposes, queer form means challenging the primacy of the
visual, which has too often been a site for pernicious power
relations […]. At their base, such operations of surveillance and
classification rely on the concept of immutable difference, on sharp
boundaries, and on the possibility of exhaustively knowing the other
[…]. We see queer form as an aesthetics that moves persistently
around the visual, thereby avoiding this flattening. To the extent
that form operates behind the scenes as ideological impulse and
materiality, queer formal practices can resist the dictates of
transparency normally required of non-normative subjects by
illuminating the unseen. In this way it not only troubles the
epistemic assurances of the visual regime, but it also asks how
shifting away from static visuality can circumnavigate questions of
objectification. A move toward the diffusely sensual, and away from
the linearity of visual gazing, articulates difference in terms that
are not about dominance or norms, but that underscore the importance
of thinking with other modes of knowing, theorizing, and
experiencing. Queer form is about other ways of understanding
relationships to power and relationships to being. 232-3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My work strives to show how Queer Form as an “aesthetics” can
productively mirror and offer openings to study digital forms. I’ve
been plumbing this connection between “queer formalism” and
“deformance” — “queer formalism” is a term from Tyler Bradway’s
&lt;em&gt;PMLA&lt;/em&gt; article, “Queer Narrative Theory and the Relationality of
Form”; and “deformance” I take from Jerome McGann and Lisa Samuel’s
foundational essay, “Deformance and Interpretation.” Bradway describes
that, while Queer has been seen as a disrupter of form, such as
narrative form by disrupting chronology, linearity, or “reproductive
futurism,” etc, Queerness is still accessible through form. He admits
that “Queerness tells no tales. It only disturbs, troubles, or
shatters them” (711). However, taking Amin, Musser, and Perez’s ideas
about form as a strategy for opacity, he points out that “Queerness is
shaped by passionate attachments to certain forms,” such as the “the
vivid interleavings of narrative and social theory in Gloria
Anzaldua’s &lt;em&gt;Borderlands&lt;/em&gt;, Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick’s &lt;em&gt;Tendencies&lt;/em&gt;, or
Jose Esteban Munoz’s &lt;em&gt;Cruising Utopia&lt;/em&gt;” (712). In my reading, McGann
and Samuels take a similar stance in their turn to digital forms, by
valuating any formal shift in text (such as from print to digital) for
the way it opens interpretive possiblities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><category term="TEI" /><category term="queer form" /><category term="queer formalism" /><category term="deformance" /><category term="revising" /><summary type="html">The work on chapter two has been taking longer than I thought- there were three weeks of heavy revision in October/November, where I made the following changes at the request of my peer reviewers. Then a round of copyediting, which is done, and the final round of proofreading, to be completed next week, after which the thing will finally go to press. The major revisions included:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Drafting Chapter Two</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/drafting-chap-two/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Drafting Chapter Two" /><published>2021-09-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-09-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/drafting-chap-two</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/drafting-chap-two/">&lt;p&gt;The goal for the summer was to address the remaining small edits of
the first chapter and to complete a readable draft of the second
chapter by August 31. I managed to make that goal, though a few days
late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to repurpose most of my seminar paper on &lt;em&gt;Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt;,
about 15 pages or so, into this chapter. They formed the background
discussion of the manuscript and the analysis of the revisions in the
first chapter. Then came a period of heavy writing, about two weeks,
where I created new sections on “Queer Historiography,” “TEI,” an
introduction and conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper explores how to use TEI to mark up the homoerotic elements
that Wilde revised and obscured in the first chapter of the &lt;em&gt;Dorian
Gray&lt;/em&gt; manuscript. I first examine the question of perservation in the
field of Textual Editing, drawing out a debate between the more
“conservative” (favoring preservation via the discovery of authorial
intention) and the more “productive” approach which fully develops
with the advent of digital media (and uses digital media to explore
productive permutations and presentations of textual material). Then I
bring another scholarly debate for comparison, which is the debate on
the proper methodology for Queer Historiography, that is, whether it
is possible or desirable for critics in the present to adequately know
queerness in the past. I isolate one perspective, that of Heather Love
and what she calls “feeling backward,” which attends to the past
without trying to redeem or rescue it, as a guide toward developing my
editing methodology. I then turn to the manuscript itself, to examine
and analyze the changes that Wilde imposes on the homoerotic elements
from the first chapter. My reading here highlights a number of
“themes” that reveal what Wilde’s pen worked to suppress, and include:
“tension,” “affection,” “passion,” “beauty,” and “fatality.”  Finally,
I turn to the TEI (Text Encoding Initiative) language itself, pointing
out its characteristics relevant to my project, such as one seeming
contradiction between the potential for customization (TEI allows for
researchers to create custom tags according to the needs of the
project) and the constrained nature of the tags which nonetheless
impose a level of legibility and fixity on the text. I conclude by
demonstrating how my method marks up homoerotic elements, although not
in a way that fixes them or makes them more legible to
researchers. Rather, the markup serves to index moments where the
tagging and labelling fails to capture how the homoerotic themes
appear and function in the text. Here, the lesson from Queer
Historiography comes to the fore: the act of marking up a text, which
can never fully capture the queer elements of the text, really
functions more as a tool for discovering those moments that elude
containment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having submitted this draft for review, I don’t think there’s much to
do with it now but wait for revisions. In the meantime, I will go back
to the first chapter (for the third time!) to get it ready for Matt’s
eyes. Hopefully a couple of weeks will help get it into “readable” form.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><category term="TEI" /><category term="text encoding" /><category term="Oscar Wilde" /><category term="Dorian Gray" /><category term="Manuscript" /><summary type="html">The goal for the summer was to address the remaining small edits of the first chapter and to complete a readable draft of the second chapter by August 31. I managed to make that goal, though a few days late.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Revisting Chapter One</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/revisiting-ch-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Revisting Chapter One" /><published>2021-04-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-04-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/revisiting-ch-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/revisiting-ch-1/">&lt;p&gt;After letting the draft sit for a while, slightly traumatized by the
hectic process of wrapping it up over the winter, I was pleasantly
surprised by my perspective on it now. The argument that I found
discouragingly convoluted still reads as a bit messy but also
intriguing, particularly in the way it interweaveas deformance and
performativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I really should be talking to my advisor about it. Even
if the prose isn’t ready to share, the ideas are workable. Before
that, though, I’m going to give myself a week to revise some things
that stand out to me, in this order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;add more up front on the technology of Distant Reading, how it
works, a kind of media archaeology of the tech.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flesh out the final analysis of Woolf’s text (which depends on the
specifics of Disant Reading tech).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;find a way to structurally integrate the close reading of Woolf’s
text. Interweave with the intro? Maybe starting with a meditation on
gender?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other news, my abstract on this chapter was accepted by the ACH
conference. One other abstract (on my second chapter, which I am now
in the process of researching) was accepted at MLA, as well as a book
article on the same chapter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><category term="text analysis" /><category term="queer distant reading" /><category term="revision" /><summary type="html">After letting the draft sit for a while, slightly traumatized by the hectic process of wrapping it up over the winter, I was pleasantly surprised by my perspective on it now. The argument that I found discouragingly convoluted still reads as a bit messy but also intriguing, particularly in the way it interweaveas deformance and performativity.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Closing Up Chapter One</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/closing-up-chapter-one/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Closing Up Chapter One" /><published>2021-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/closing-up-chapter-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/closing-up-chapter-one/">&lt;p&gt;Even though I still need to finalize the conclusion (and add a final
example of text analysis), I’m deeming the first draft of my first
chapter complete. It’s been nearly a year, and the thing has taken so
many shapes, texts, interventions in the meantime. Although there’s
still a little more work to do, fleshing out some text analysis with
Python, the thing is being set aside. It doesn’t feel totally done –
in fact I feel slightly guilty for setting it aside – but I know that
any attempt to finalize it right now will just have to be revised once
I progress through other chapters and my intervention develops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is an abstract for the project, which I recently submitted to
the [ACH conference][https://ach2021.ach.org/]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Queer Distant Reading: Quantifying Gender in Woolf’s “Orlando”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project explores how Queer Studies and quantitative text analysis
might work together to analyze queer identity in 20th and 21st century
literature. In recent years, practitioners of distant reading have
been grappling with the problem of quantifying gender and sexuality,
among other aspects of minority identity. My project intervenes in
this debate by exploring one of the stickier aspects of distant
reading–reproducibility. I trace a genealogy of reproducibility from
distant reading’s inception in Franco Moretti’s call for a
“falsifiable criticism” to more recent experiments in which
researchers “reproduce” their assumptions about social categories in
the results of their analysis. However, rather than condemn the
reproducible, this project unpacks its radical potential by reworking
it to engage with Judith Butler’s concept of performativity. Bringing
Butler’s foundational ideas about “performative citation” from Queer
Theory to distant reading, I propose a methodology that achieves
displacement through repetition, subversion through iteration, and
resistance from within the flattening processes of
quantification. This method illustrates how the iterative practice of
analyzing text computationally can surface new textual structures and
resignify elements of that text. I demonstrate this critical method
with an analysis of Virginia Woolf’s text, Orlando: A Biography (1928)
to explore how the terms “man” and “woman” can be re-signified to
multiply our already complex understanding of gender in that
text. This method harnesses the reductions of reproducibility within
text analytical methods in order to advance the study of queer
identity in Queer Studies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><category term="text analysis" /><category term="queer distant reading" /><summary type="html">Even though I still need to finalize the conclusion (and add a final example of text analysis), I’m deeming the first draft of my first chapter complete. It’s been nearly a year, and the thing has taken so many shapes, texts, interventions in the meantime. Although there’s still a little more work to do, fleshing out some text analysis with Python, the thing is being set aside. It doesn’t feel totally done – in fact I feel slightly guilty for setting it aside – but I know that any attempt to finalize it right now will just have to be revised once I progress through other chapters and my intervention develops.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fantasy of the Falsifiable</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/fantasy-of-the-falsifiable/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fantasy of the Falsifiable" /><published>2020-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/fantasy-of-the-falsifiable</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/fantasy-of-the-falsifiable/">&lt;p&gt;In the past three months, this chapter has taken on a whole new
form. I had a meeting with my dissertation workshop in late October
that revealed to me how I was writing around the argument I wanted to
make, which is about deconstructing (in NKM’s words) “the fantasy of
the falsifiable.” So I cut about half of what I had already written,
the sections on the digital, queerness, and touch, and moved that to
an introductory chapter. What remained was the section where I
critique “reproducible” criticism, and that was pretty much it. Around
this section, I’ve written another on textual scholarship and
deformance, and one on queer performance. I’m now working on the final
section of the chapter, where I synthesize aspects from deformance and
preformance to present a new approach for “queer” text analysis. After
that, I will write up a quick intro that begins be presenting a
critique of the falsifiable, which I position as forerunner to the
reproducible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The burden of the chapter is to describe how to do text analysis in a
way that attends to queer concepts of performativity, and how that
method enhances the critical process. It begins by debunking the
fantasy of falsifiable criticism, presenting a critique of moretti’s
methodology and stylistic approach (eventually with accompanying text
analysis). It then goes into a critique of current distant reading
practices, discussing Ted Underwood, Nan Z. Da, to emphasize how these
practices can often reproduce the critic’s assumptions. This section
also discusses the work of Johanna Drucker and Richard Jean So,
emphasizing that their methods do a good job deconstructing social
categories. While this deconstruction is important, I’m interested in
analysis of text that disrupts what we know about these literary
materials by producing new structures, or formalizations of these
texts. Then, I go into a history of textual scholarship, focusing
particularly on the work of Jerome McGann, Tanya Clement, and
Katherine Bode, who offer a deformative and speculative understanding
of critical analysis that is useful for my proposal. Then, I dip into
Queer Theory, in particular Judith Butler’s concepts of performativity
and citation, which lend an understanding to the ways that critical
processes can subvert dominant structures through iteration, or
“performative citation.” This notion of displacement through
repetition is applied back to text analysis to illustrate how the
iterative process of analyzing text can surface new textual structures
that re-signify certain elements of that text. The chapter ends with
my reading of Virginia Woolf’s /Orlando/, to show how our
understanding of “man” and “woman” in that text is re-signified
through this kind of text analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next steps, is to continue to explore /Orlando/ and Moretti in Python
(though not for too long) so I can write up this final section and the
introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost there!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><category term="dissertation workshop" /><category term="feedback" /><category term="revision" /><summary type="html">In the past three months, this chapter has taken on a whole new form. I had a meeting with my dissertation workshop in late October that revealed to me how I was writing around the argument I wanted to make, which is about deconstructing (in NKM’s words) “the fantasy of the falsifiable.” So I cut about half of what I had already written, the sections on the digital, queerness, and touch, and moved that to an introductory chapter. What remained was the section where I critique “reproducible” criticism, and that was pretty much it. Around this section, I’ve written another on textual scholarship and deformance, and one on queer performance. I’m now working on the final section of the chapter, where I synthesize aspects from deformance and preformance to present a new approach for “queer” text analysis. After that, I will write up a quick intro that begins be presenting a critique of the falsifiable, which I position as forerunner to the reproducible.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Feedback on Chapter One Intro</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/feedback-chap1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feedback on Chapter One Intro" /><published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/feedback-chap1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/feedback-chap1/">&lt;p&gt;Last week I shared the intro to my first chapter with my dissertation
workshop. Below is the feedback I received, indicating points for
revision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, positives: people are really compelled by my topic and close
readings. They appreciate the ways I am engaging DH and Queer Theory
around the trope of “touch.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, for the criticism:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three heavy footnotes in the beginning are tripping people up, a
bit overwhelming. Work on spreading this out. In doing so, luxuriate
in the idea of how digital etymology relates to the idea of touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;clarify specific terms/concepts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who is &lt;strong&gt;Matt Kirschenbaum&lt;/strong&gt;? Characterize him a little bit for
outsiders. Situate myself in relation to him. Also consider taking
out or reducing the footnote on materiality, because it’s tripping
people up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explain why I am choosing this word &lt;strong&gt;formalization&lt;/strong&gt; to describe a
construct. What does this term do that “construct” cannot do?
Another sentence on what I mean here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What Queer theory am I using, at &lt;strong&gt;reconsolidation&lt;/strong&gt;. The
abstraction of the queer subject. (related to the issue of
positioning myself w/ regard to queer theory: The ways that queer
subjectivity is constructed differently in early poststructrualism,
as opposed to affect theory. Affect theory tries to bring the body
back, thinking to Sara Ahmed vs Foucault). In addition to defining
my position/sources, also consider how “queer” can be reclaimed by
those it is meant to oppress (Butler, ‘Critically Queer’).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the sensual fullness of a lack&lt;/strong&gt;: see butler on beauvoir and
irigaray, two women together as a double lack, in gender
trouble. /When our two lips touch/, Irigaray&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;see how &lt;strong&gt;haptic&lt;/strong&gt; is being deployed in other disciplines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what do I mean by &lt;strong&gt;touch as abstraction&lt;/strong&gt; on page 3? The physical
experience of touch may be an abstraction, or abstracted, but it is
not experienced as such. Jacob: “Touch often registers as painful
immediacy”. See Ann Cvetkovitch’s writing on Stone Butch Blues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on page 3, I’m making sweeping claims about the &lt;strong&gt;Queer
Subject&lt;/strong&gt;. Is there a single queer subject, a queer subjectivity? Do
the narrators demonstrate this? If so, what is that kind of queer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More broadly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how does the digital relate to the &lt;strong&gt;body&lt;/strong&gt;? how does it change the
body? how does queerness do this? –&amp;gt; Butler’s points about how a
body doesn’t come into being until contact in /Bodies that Matter/.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what am I doing with &lt;strong&gt;touch more broadly&lt;/strong&gt;? why is this chapter
about touch?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emphasize that I’m doing this &lt;strong&gt;new thing&lt;/strong&gt;, this new field. DH can
help us theorize the queer; and queer can help us understand the
Digital.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clarify the relationship between &lt;strong&gt;removal, touch, and grasp&lt;/strong&gt;. How
are these distinct?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In close readings, &lt;strong&gt;the various registers of touch&lt;/strong&gt; are at odds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I start the chapter by saying that queer and the digital are related
through touch, then I assert that it is a troubled relationship to
touch. Make it clear at the start that I’m thinking about touch as a
complicated activity/phenomenon, not touch as always making
contact.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How the implications of touch are slightly different or opposite to
each other across the close readings. One is frustrated touch and
one touch opens up. Establish the connection between the two.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There’s a tension between literal touch (touching the text) and
figurative touch (touch as a trope, touch via sight). Emphasize and
distinguish the difference between touch as a figure within the text
and as a means of engaging without the text. Additionally, on the
literal side, how is this touch (clicking through) different from
turning the page?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;revise the close reading of /waves/ to include analysis of the beam
routine. How is touch operating? there is no touch in this scene.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the paradox of touch: the untouchable is good — it is a paradox.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the paradox of touch: touching w/o touching&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revise close-reading of /Waves/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;people found it confusing regarding “touch” and doesn’t cohere as
nicely as /Confessions/ with my chapter argument.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emphasize dynamics of the beam routine, the not touching in that
episode paralleling the not touching of /Confessions/.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;explain clearly the removal between reader and text not only in the
level of narrative form but also in the materiality of the substance
of the story, the codes and computation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More readings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on Munoz –&amp;gt; also think about Raymond Williams, and structures of
feelings which will help you elaborate on emergence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;will narratology help me clarify some of the terms on page 6, on the
close readings of /Waves/? Mieke Bal perhaps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><category term="dissertation workshop" /><category term="feedback" /><category term="revision" /><summary type="html">Last week I shared the intro to my first chapter with my dissertation workshop. Below is the feedback I received, indicating points for revision.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Zooming out of Chapter One</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/zooming-out-of-chapter-one/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zooming out of Chapter One" /><published>2020-07-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/zooming-out-of-chapter-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/zooming-out-of-chapter-one/">&lt;p&gt;About a week ago I converted my chapter document into a word
doc. Until now, I’ve only been engaging with the draft on through the
text editor Emacs using Org Mode, an amazing format that allows you to
collapse paragraphs and outlines to make writing cleaner and more
navigable. As a result, however, I didn’t have a sense of how long my
document was until I opened it in Word. Turns out I have 34 pages
single spaced. And I still need to draft what I think will take up
about one third of the chapter. Clearly, some revision and
reorganization is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I took the week to go through the entire doc, writing concise
notes and outlines of my work so far, and flagging things that still
need to be done. Below is an image of the first 2/3 or so of the
chapter draft, showing the outline and flags for specific sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/org_outline.png&quot; alt=&quot;image of chapter outline in emacs org
mode&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After taking this time to step back and see the big picture, I feel a
lot better about the work that I’ve already achieved, though almost
all of the paragraphs need some work in revising and refining. There’s
still a long way to go, but there’s also an arc here, a form of my
argument that takes shape despite the gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I’m going to set some goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;first, the next week (July 27) I will draft the final third of the
chapter. This will be hard work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the next two weeks, (august 3 &amp;amp; 10) will be spent on cleaning up the
first three sections, “intro to touch” and “queerness as untouchable,”
and “solutions.” This is to prepare for sharing those pages with my
Undercommons writing group in mid-August.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;then, starting August 17 until September, I’ll revise the rest of
the chapter, fulfilling any lingering TODOs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;following this schedule, by the end of August I will hopefully have
something, even if not perfect, to send to Matt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I revise, I find myself more and more myred in the various
definitions of queerness. It will be important to keep the following
in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being queer is, at its core, a desire for connection—with oneself
or with others—that is continually thwarted by the oppression,
categories, and heteronormativity of dominant culture. Queerness which
we can only engage within formalized or opaque structures—the formal
experiments of queer writers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The “untouchable” denotes a state of &lt;em&gt;suspended knowledge&lt;/em&gt; (about queer
subjectivity and experience) that allows me to then turn to &lt;em&gt;feeling
and affect&lt;/em&gt; as epistemological methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><category term="dissertation" /><category term="org-mode" /><category term="revision" /><summary type="html">About a week ago I converted my chapter document into a word doc. Until now, I’ve only been engaging with the draft on through the text editor Emacs using Org Mode, an amazing format that allows you to collapse paragraphs and outlines to make writing cleaner and more navigable. As a result, however, I didn’t have a sense of how long my document was until I opened it in Word. Turns out I have 34 pages single spaced. And I still need to draft what I think will take up about one third of the chapter. Clearly, some revision and reorganization is necessary.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Drafting the Intro</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/close-reading-intro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Drafting the Intro" /><published>2020-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/close-reading-intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/close-reading-intro/">&lt;p&gt;My past two posts have been clarifying the concept of “untouchable”
and how it functions in relation to queerness. “Untouchable” denotes a
state of &lt;em&gt;suspended knowledge&lt;/em&gt; (about queer subjectivity and
experience) that allows me to then turn to &lt;em&gt;feeling and affect&lt;/em&gt; as
epistemological methods.
    - First, I worked out a definition of “untouchable” as the raw
      data about queer subjectivity and experience that cannot be
      quantified. (later in the chapter, I will explain that in order
      to engage (or “interface”) with this data, we need abstraction
      and formalization.
	- Then, I looked for analogies of the “untouchable” in other
      fields (history and science) that display the impulse to verify,
      correct, or recover. In literary studies, this impulse for
      satisfaction is observed in “paranoid” or “suspicious” reading
      practices, which attempt to find “hidden meaning” in texts in a
      way that constrains inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These past two weeks, I’ve been working on the introduction, because
it occurs to me that I need a solid definition of queerness before
moving on to describe how queerness is untouchable. So I defined the
core condition of queerness being &lt;strong&gt;“the desire for touching,” a
desire that is ultimately frustrated, deferred, or eluded&lt;/strong&gt; (analogous
to Jose Munoz’s concept of queer horizon, the state of being “not yet
here”). Being queer is, at its core, a desire for connection—with
oneself or with others—that is continually thwarted by the
oppression, categories, and heteronormativity of dominant culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “desire for touching,” without being able to fully touch, as the
definition of queerness, is also where the digital and queer
intersect. Digital media creates the illusion that we have access to
data, to information, but all we have access to is a &lt;em&gt;formalized&lt;/em&gt;
relationship to that data. We encounter the digital object through
mediation, through an interface, mice, GUIs, keyboards, etc. It is the
same with queernes, which we can only engage within formalized or
opaque structures—the formal experiments of queer writers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m trying to begin the chapter with this meditation on the
intersection of the digital and queerness. Right now, I’m doing so by
providing a few close readings, right at the start, which define
queerness as a thwarted desire for touching. In the example I’ve
chosen, by Jordy Rosenberg’s &lt;em&gt;Confessions of the Fox&lt;/em&gt;, I use an
evocative quote that characterizes sexual desire not on touch, but how
precluding touch activates other sensations that are more physical,
more intense, than touch. Then I jump to a hypertext novella, &lt;em&gt;These
Waves of Girls&lt;/em&gt; by Caitlin Fisher, and discuss how the narrative pull
of clicking through the text enacts a desire for closure or
understanding that is never fully satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It occurs to me now that I need to go a little more into the &lt;em&gt;Waves&lt;/em&gt;
example, include a bit of media archaeology, the formal and forensic
(Matt Kirschenbaum) levels of materiality, and a bit about how
hypertext works, to fully round out this point. I’m drawing a parallel
between what Rosenberg is doing with refusing touch and what Fisher is
doing by frustrating touch. They are both searching for alternative
modes of connections, modes that active a fuller sensorium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the introduction might be structured thus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an opening statement on how touch relates to queerness and the
digital&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a definition of queerness as deferred desire for touching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing two case studies that demonstrate how queerness engages
this idea of deffered touch in text and digital media.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this introduction, which is only meant to pique interest and
 set ideas into motion, I will move on to exploring the “untouchable”
 state of queerness in depth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><category term="dissertation" /><category term="rosenberg" /><category term="fisher" /><category term="munoz" /><summary type="html">My past two posts have been clarifying the concept of “untouchable” and how it functions in relation to queerness. “Untouchable” denotes a state of suspended knowledge (about queer subjectivity and experience) that allows me to then turn to feeling and affect as epistemological methods. - First, I worked out a definition of “untouchable” as the raw data about queer subjectivity and experience that cannot be quantified. (later in the chapter, I will explain that in order to engage (or “interface”) with this data, we need abstraction and formalization. - Then, I looked for analogies of the “untouchable” in other fields (history and science) that display the impulse to verify, correct, or recover. In literary studies, this impulse for satisfaction is observed in “paranoid” or “suspicious” reading practices, which attempt to find “hidden meaning” in texts in a way that constrains inquiry.</summary></entry></feed>