<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-01-24T18:37:23-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Queer Tools</title><subtitle>Notes Toward a Dissertation</subtitle><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><entry><title type="html">Reflections from GC-DRI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/digital-research-institute/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections from GC-DRI" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/digital-research-institute</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/digital-research-institute/">&lt;p&gt;The past few days we have been running our annual &lt;a href=&quot;https://gcdri.commons.gc.cuny.edu/&quot;&gt;Digital Research
Institute&lt;/a&gt; at the Graduate Center
Digital Initiatives. I’ve taught three sessions of python, and
supported sessions on Text Analysis, as well as helping out in Command
Line, Git/Github, and attended Mapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’ve found, or realized once again, is how much my approach
toward data and method informs my interest in DH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I watched the Text Analysis workshop unfold, the most striking
realization was the preconceptions and biases we bring into our
inferences. We might make certain assumptions about analysis. For
example, in Natural Language Toolkit’s (NLTK) &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;similar()&lt;/code&gt; method, we
measure what words are similar to any other word. In the analysis
below, we see what words are associated to “love” across two different
texts, &lt;em&gt;Moby Dick&lt;/em&gt; (text1) and &lt;em&gt;Sense And Sensibility&lt;/em&gt; (text2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/love-similar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finding words that are similar to &amp;quot;love&amp;quot; in *Moby Dick* and *Sense
and Sensibility*&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Melville, love is associated with the strong natural forces,
having to do with nature (“sea,” “whale,” “fear”) and men, male bodies
(“head,” “hand,” “him,” “me”). In Austen, the word love has
associations with domestic life, family and specific people (“sister,”
“mother,” “elinor,” “marianne”). Both Melville and Austen share “head”
and “him,” though Austen also has “heart” (while Melvill has “hand”)
and “her.” In Austen, affect is associated with “affection,” while
Melville associates it with “fear.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder how our analysis might change when we know the text is
written by a woman. What kinds of conclusions are we tempted to draw?
Presumably, that love for Austen is associated with familial
affection, and for Melville, with awe of nature and man, and that
these differences indicate gender differences. To be overly reductive:
women find love in the home, and men out in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this desire to draw conclusions isn’t the right approach, or at
least it’s not the most interesting to me. I am not doing text
analysis to answer a question. I am doing it to arrive at the
question, which is a way to keep the literary conversation going (see
Stephen Ramsay, &lt;em&gt;Algorithmic Criticism&lt;/em&gt;). During the session, Rafa
said something that reinforced this idea, that “text analysis is just
playing with lists.”  That idea of play is the space I want to stay
in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of play, I’m thinking a lot about how we can try to
queer or mess around with some of the reductions of “cleaning text.”
Obviously, the more and more you clean your data, that you simplify
and regularize strings, the easier it is to see the relationships
between them (Moretti: “where &lt;em&gt;distance&lt;/em&gt; is a condition of
&lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt;”). Lemmatizing words, stemming them, removing stopwords
and punctuation, are ways of reducing the complexity of data in order
to make comparisons between them and draw conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m proposing that we take a closer look at some of the data that
is often ignored in text analysis, which are “stopwords.” Stopwords
are text that are commonly used and thought to be semantically void,
such as articles and prepositions. I compiled a list of stopwords from
one of my favorite texts,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks02/0200331.txt&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Orlando: A Biography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Virginia
Woolf:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;['for', 'there', 'be', 'no', 'of', 'his', 'the', 'of', 'the',
'did', 'to', 'it', 'was', 'in', 'the', 'of', 'at', 'the', 'of', 'a',
'which', 'from', 'the', 'was', 'the', 'of', 'an', 'and', 'more', 'or',
'the', 'of', 'for', 'the', 'and', 'a', 'or', 'of', 'the', 'on', 'a',
'or', 'his', 'had', 'it', 'from', 'the', 'of', 'a', 'who', 'had',
'up', 'under', 'the', 'in', 'the', 'of', 'and', 'now', 'it', 'in',
'the', 'which', 'through', 'the', 'of', 'the', 'of', 'the', 'who',
'had', 'him', 'had', 'in', 'of', 'and', 'and', 'by', 'and', 'they',
'had', 'of', 'off', 'and', 'them', 'to', 'from', 'the', 'too', 'he',
'he', 'was', 'only', 'and', 'too', 'to', 'with', 'them', 'in', 'or']
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who is familiar with &lt;em&gt;Orlando&lt;/em&gt; will notice the cadence of the
first few sentences in these lines. I’m interested in how these words,
often overlooked, can give us some insight into the movement of the
text. Can prepositions help to suggest the energy or tone of a passage?
How might they be compared to what William James describes in “Stream
of Thought” as the the “moments of flight” between “images” or “resting places”
(typically conveyed by nouns and adjectives)? I don’t know if this
line of thinking will lead anywhere, but it seems like an interesting
project.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">The past few days we have been running our annual Digital Research Institute at the Graduate Center Digital Initiatives. I’ve taught three sessions of python, and supported sessions on Text Analysis, as well as helping out in Command Line, Git/Github, and attended Mapping.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">M– asks me some questions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/m-questions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="M-- asks me some questions" /><published>2019-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/m-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/m-questions/">&lt;p&gt;Submitted my prospectus to the English office today. It’s been a long
process—three months, three drafts, two reviews in Dissertation
Workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I changed the introduction, going more directly into Queer DH. I also
narrowed down the focus of the main paragraphs after the intro:
reading method, Life Writing, Cyborgs, and added a paragraph on
“Queer,” used in three ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Queer Methods (reading practices, relationality—touching but not
touching)- A reading method, searching for moments of misfitting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Queer Materiality (queer subjects, digital media)- At the level of
the body and the computer, looking at the materiality of “mind” and
“computation”. Close reading the man and the machine. A rubric for
engagement, human-machine interactions, the cyborg.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Queer Texts (life writing: memoir &amp;amp; journals, manuscripts)- Formal
experiments of literature that engage experience and cognition as
embodied processes, modes of perception that are
enworlded. Figurations of the digital.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also added a paragraph, “Toward Disability,” which elaborates the
aesthetic encounter between reader and object, the logical conclusion
of a queer relationality, my reading method. Here, I concretize my
interest in “electronic editing schemas that mark elusive
subjectivities, digital annotation tools that visualize affective
responses to reading, and archival digitization efforts that animate
the past.” I also added a paragraph introducting the chapter
descriptions and tying together the threads around this central
question: “How do our current digital tools facilitate queer
encounters with literature?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a meeting last week, M– asked me some questions that helped me to
whittle down my motives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would I summarize my project in one sentence?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About looking at ways that technology disrupts our expectations. How
it prompts the incommensurable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What am I most interested in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The materiality of media, and of human bodies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">Submitted my prospectus to the English office today. It’s been a long process—three months, three drafts, two reviews in Dissertation Workshop.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Certificate Accomplished</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/submitted-itp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Certificate Accomplished" /><published>2019-12-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/submitted-itp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/submitted-itp/">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I submitted my final paper for the ITP (Interactive
Technology and Pedagogy) certificate program. I started working on
this project in the spring of 2018, when I theorized the purpose of
building and using a (digital) multi-color highlighter to teach
close-reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, I’ve built the highlighter (see my detailed &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gofilipa/digital_annotation/blob/master/notes/development_notes.md&quot;&gt;development
notes&lt;/a&gt;)
and spent a lot more time thinking and writing about how color and
nonverbal methods can help teach critical reading and writing. I’ve
been interested in critiquing Educational Technology (EdTech) tools,
which track and quantify student performance in ways that automate and
standardize learning. I wonder how we can build tools that refuse to
follow these trends of data collection. In the paper, I use the
multi-color highlighter to bring edtech into conversation with
neuroscience, exploring how digital annotation engages embodied
reading practices that subvert edtech’s attempts to measure and
quantify student reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper, as it stands, has some work to do. First, I need to tie
these threads of EdTech and neuroscience more firmly together. I also
need to smooth out the interweaving of my tool’s development (linked
above) to the body of the paper. The goal with inserting the dev notes
throughout the paper is to make my coding work more visible, signaling
to the nontechnical reader some of the confusions and suspensions of
knowledge necessary for this kind of labor, that occur regardless of
technical proficiency. That’s a lot of work to do already, but the
most important task is to finally use this tool in a classroom,
allowing my students to play around with it and inspire further
developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the big obstacle. I cannot use the tool in a classroom until I
get some kind of server authentication for storing and retrieving
annotations. I had a meeting last week with the Hypothes.is
team, and they cannot support the data model of multi-color
annotations, which is understandable. I’m meeting with another of
their developers next week, individually, and I think he can help me
at least to understand the server-side of things so I can potentially
make my own database to store annotations. We will see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more I think about this, however, the more I wish that I had
chosen something less complicated than Hypothes.is to work with. This
tool is much too complex for my purposes, as I’m not interested in
tagging, or even commenting at all. I only need &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalfellows.commons.gc.cuny.edu/2019/10/10/toward-the-end-of-a-digital-project-reflections-on-starting-over/&quot;&gt;a minimal
highlighter&lt;/a&gt;,
a bare-bones highlighter. This kind of tool (I think) would
short-circuit the attempts to track and quantify student performance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">Yesterday I submitted my final paper for the ITP (Interactive Technology and Pedagogy) certificate program. I started working on this project in the spring of 2018, when I theorized the purpose of building and using a (digital) multi-color highlighter to teach close-reading.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Is This Useful?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/explain-yourself/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Is This Useful?" /><published>2019-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/explain-yourself</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/explain-yourself/">&lt;p&gt;Last week I had a dissertation workshop where I presented a rough
draft of my chapter on Social Annotation. I was feeling pretty
vulnerable about it. Not only is the draft in its infancy, but it also
combines a few disciplines that aren’t typical for projects in English
studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give some background—I’m developing a digital annotation tool
that has a multi-color highlighter for teaching purposes. I’m hoping
that the colors will help students to engage their immediate and
embodied responses to reading, which happen prior to their
articulation in language. Basically, I’m hoping that using colors will
allow readers to mark their reactions to reading by assigning certain
reactions to specific colors. The point, for me, is to explore
alternative kinds of annotation, particularly annotation that short
circuits verbalized forms of response. My paper on this project (which
will be fully drafted once I use the tool in the classroom)
interweaves my narrative of the tool’s technical development with
discourses on educational technology and neuroscience. I’m trying to
show the ways that current annotation tools track or quantify student
data, and how looking at reading from a neuroscientific lense,
particularly from the perspective of embodied cognition, opens up the
way we understand students’ engagement with text. To better display
this engagement, I created the highlighter with really low color
opacities that facilitates layering. I imagine that different readers
will highlight with different colors over the same piece of text. My
idea is that the color-highlighter’s layering capability will create a
kind of “heatmap” of the text, which manifests in new color
combinations. This palimpsest of readings will (I hope) show student
reactions in contrast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the feedback I got from the group was really useful. There
were comments about the structure, foregrounding the experimental
nature of the project, and rethinking how I interweave my development
notes (which everyone agreed should be included). There were also
specific terms and concepts I need to clarify, like embodiment (what
do I mean by “prediscursive” and what kind of affect theory is this)
and color frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most challenging comment was about stakes. One of the workshop
participants went on at length about needing to explain why this tool
is useful. Here were some of the questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What do I want out of this tool?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What am I doing that’s different from using actual highlighters in
books?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why should instructors care which neurons are firing?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why is the student’s affective experience important?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Who is my audience? Which conversations do I want to insert myself
into?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to answer some of these questions in the moment. Mainly my
answer for the “why” is that if we [English scholars] don’t guide this
conversation it will be guided for us, by the tech companies. If we
[the educators] don’t think about how our tools work we will use them
uncritically, and our students will become a source of data collection
rather than aesthetic production. I have some language to this effect
in the introduction, but I guess it’s understated. I also tend to
assume that everybody thinks like me and already knows that edtech is
evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, afterward, I got to thinking about it. And how absurd it is
that I was asked to defend the utility of my work. Nobody else in the
workshop is being asked these questions—at least not that I have
noticed. Only my project, the sole technical project, has this
burden. Why should I have to explain myself, when my colleagues, who
are mostly doing non traditional work on archives, melancholia, music,
composition studies, ventriloquisim, aren’t being asked to do the
same?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though the majority of my classmates’ projects aren’t
“traditional,” there’s an implicit agreement that the exploratory
nature of their scholarship is inherently important. Their choices
about objects of study or methods aren’t questioned. Why should I have
to explain my decisions? Why can’t I just tell you what I’m thinking?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">Last week I had a dissertation workshop where I presented a rough draft of my chapter on Social Annotation. I was feeling pretty vulnerable about it. Not only is the draft in its infancy, but it also combines a few disciplines that aren’t typical for projects in English studies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Code snippets in a blog post</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/code-snippets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Code snippets in a blog post" /><published>2019-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/code-snippets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/code-snippets/">&lt;p&gt;This post demonstrate the use of code snippets in the theme. The code snippets are powered by &lt;a href=&quot;http://pygments.org/&quot;&gt;Pygments&lt;/a&gt; and the code theme that is been used in Reverie is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://draculatheme.com/&quot;&gt;Draula&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a raw snippet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;hello world
123
This is a text snippet
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a PHP snippet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-php highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;?php&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Hello, World!'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a JavaScript snippet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-js highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;add&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;minus&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;add&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;200&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// 300&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;minus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;200&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// -100&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Python snippet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;say_hello&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;hello world!&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;say_hello&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;hello world!&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">This post demonstrate the use of code snippets in the theme. The code snippets are powered by Pygments and the code theme that is been used in Reverie is called Draula.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/no-title-posts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2019-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/no-title-posts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/no-title-posts/">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, your post just stands for itself and doesn’t need a title. And that’s fine, too!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">Sometimes, your post just stands for itself and doesn’t need a title. And that’s fine, too!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some articles are just so short that we’ve to make the footer stick</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/super-short-article/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some articles are just so short that we've to make the footer stick" /><published>2019-07-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/super-short-article</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/super-short-article/">&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipisicing elit, sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi ut aliquip ex ea commodo consequat. Duis aute irure dolor in reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. Excepteur sint occaecat cupidatat non proident, sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollit anim id est laborum.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipisicing elit, sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi ut aliquip ex ea commodo consequat. Duis aute irure dolor in reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. Excepteur sint occaecat cupidatat non proident, sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollit anim id est laborum.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This post demonstrates post content styles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/this-post-demonstrates-post-content-styles/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This post demonstrates post content styles" /><published>2019-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/this-post-demonstrates-post-content-styles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/this-post-demonstrates-post-content-styles/">&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Fusce bibendum neque eget nunc mattis eu sollicitudin enim tincidunt. Vestibulum lacus tortor, ultricies id dignissim ac, bibendum in velit. Praesent varius interdum vehicula. Aenean risus libero, placerat at vestibulum eget, ultricies eu enim. Praesent nulla tortor, malesuada adipiscing adipiscing sollicitudin, adipiscing eget est.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-great-heading-h2&quot;&gt;Some great heading (h2)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proin convallis mi ac felis pharetra aliquam. Curabitur dignissim accumsan rutrum. In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum. Phasellus et hendrerit mauris. Proin eget nibh a massa vestibulum pretium. Suspendisse eu nisl a ante aliquet bibendum quis a nunc. Praesent varius interdum vehicula. Aenean risus libero, placerat at vestibulum eget, ultricies eu enim. Praesent nulla tortor, malesuada adipiscing adipiscing sollicitudin, adipiscing eget est.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;another-great-heading-h2&quot;&gt;Another great heading (h2)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Fusce bibendum neque eget nunc mattis eu sollicitudin enim tincidunt. Vestibulum lacus tortor, ultricies id dignissim ac, bibendum in velit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-great-subheading-h3&quot;&gt;Some great subheading (h3)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proin convallis mi ac felis pharetra aliquam. Curabitur dignissim accumsan rutrum. In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu. Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phasellus et hendrerit mauris. Proin eget nibh a massa vestibulum pretium. Suspendisse eu nisl a ante aliquet bibendum quis a nunc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-great-subheading-h3-1&quot;&gt;Some great subheading (h3)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Praesent varius interdum vehicula. Aenean risus libero, placerat at vestibulum eget, ultricies eu enim. Praesent nulla tortor, malesuada adipiscing adipiscing sollicitudin, adipiscing eget est.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This quote will change your life. It will reveal the secrets of the universe, and all the wonders of humanity. Don’t misuse it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Fusce bibendum neque eget nunc mattis eu sollicitudin enim tincidunt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-great-subheading-h3-2&quot;&gt;Some great subheading (h3)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vestibulum lacus tortor, ultricies id dignissim ac, bibendum in velit. Proin convallis mi ac felis pharetra aliquam. Curabitur dignissim accumsan rutrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Hello, World!&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu. Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum. Phasellus et hendrerit mauris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;you-might-want-a-sub-subheading-h4&quot;&gt;You might want a sub-subheading (h4)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu. Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum. Phasellus et hendrerit mauris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu. Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum. Phasellus et hendrerit mauris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;but-its-probably-overkill-h4&quot;&gt;But it’s probably overkill (h4)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu. Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum. Phasellus et hendrerit mauris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;oh-hai-an-unordered-list&quot;&gt;Oh hai, an unordered list!!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu. Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum. Phasellus et hendrerit mauris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First item, yo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second item, dawg&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Third item, what what?!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fourth item, fo sheezy my neezy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;oh-hai-an-ordered-list&quot;&gt;Oh hai, an ordered list!!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu. Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum. Phasellus et hendrerit mauris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First item, yo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second item, dawg&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Third item, what what?!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fourth item, fo sheezy my neezy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;headings-are-cool-h2&quot;&gt;Headings are cool! (h2)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proin eget nibh a massa vestibulum pretium. Suspendisse eu nisl a ante aliquet bibendum quis a nunc. Praesent varius interdum vehicula. Aenean risus libero, placerat at vestibulum eget, ultricies eu enim. Praesent nulla tortor, malesuada adipiscing adipiscing sollicitudin, adipiscing eget est.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Praesent nulla tortor, malesuada adipiscing adipiscing sollicitudin, adipiscing eget est.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proin eget nibh a massa vestibulum pretium. Suspendisse eu nisl a ante aliquet bibendum quis a nunc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tables&quot;&gt;Tables&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title 1&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title 2&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title 3&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title 4&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lorem ipsum dolor sit&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Fusce bibendum neque eget nunc mattis eu sollicitudin enim tincidunt. Vestibulum lacus tortor, ultricies id dignissim ac, bibendum in velit. Praesent varius interdum vehicula. Aenean risus libero, placerat at vestibulum eget, ultricies eu enim. Praesent nulla tortor, malesuada adipiscing adipiscing sollicitudin, adipiscing eget est.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some articles are just so long they deserve a really long title to see if things will break well</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/super-long-article/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some articles are just so long they deserve a really long title to see if things will break well" /><published>2019-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/super-long-article</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/super-long-article/">&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Fusce bibendum neque eget nunc mattis eu sollicitudin enim tincidunt. Vestibulum lacus tortor, ultricies id dignissim ac, bibendum in velit. Proin convallis mi ac felis pharetra aliquam. Curabitur dignissim accumsan rutrum. In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu. Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum. Phasellus et hendrerit mauris. Proin eget nibh a massa vestibulum pretium. Suspendisse eu nisl a ante aliquet bibendum quis a nunc. Praesent varius interdum vehicula. Aenean risus libero, placerat at vestibulum eget, ultricies eu enim. Praesent nulla tortor, malesuada adipiscing adipiscing sollicitudin, adipiscing eget est.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Fusce bibendum neque eget nunc mattis eu sollicitudin enim tincidunt. Vestibulum lacus tortor, ultricies id dignissim ac, bibendum in velit. Proin convallis mi ac felis pharetra aliquam. Curabitur dignissim accumsan rutrum. In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu. Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum. Phasellus et hendrerit mauris. Proin eget nibh a massa vestibulum pretium. Suspendisse eu nisl a ante aliquet bibendum quis a nunc. Praesent varius interdum vehicula. Aenean risus libero, placerat at vestibulum eget, ultricies eu enim. Praesent nulla tortor, malesuada adipiscing adipiscing sollicitudin, adipiscing eget est.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Fusce bibendum neque eget nunc mattis eu sollicitudin enim tincidunt. Vestibulum lacus tortor, ultricies id dignissim ac, bibendum in velit. Proin convallis mi ac felis pharetra aliquam. Curabitur dignissim accumsan rutrum. In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu. Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum. Phasellus et hendrerit mauris. Proin eget nibh a massa vestibulum pretium. Suspendisse eu nisl a ante aliquet bibendum quis a nunc. Praesent varius interdum vehicula. Aenean risus libero, placerat at vestibulum eget, ultricies eu enim. Praesent nulla tortor, malesuada adipiscing adipiscing sollicitudin, adipiscing eget est.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Fusce bibendum neque eget nunc mattis eu sollicitudin enim tincidunt. Vestibulum lacus tortor, ultricies id dignissim ac, bibendum in velit. Proin convallis mi ac felis pharetra aliquam. Curabitur dignissim accumsan rutrum. In arcu magna, aliquet vel pretium et, molestie et arcu. Mauris lobortis nulla et felis ullamcorper bibendum. Phasellus et hendrerit mauris. Proin eget nibh a massa vestibulum pretium. Suspendisse eu nisl a ante aliquet bibendum quis a nunc. Praesent varius interdum vehicula. Aenean risus libero, placerat at vestibulum eget, ultricies eu enim. Praesent nulla tortor, malesuada adipiscing adipiscing sollicitudin, adipiscing eget est.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing Reverie - A ridiculously elegant Jekyll theme</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/introducing-reverie-jekyll-theme/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing Reverie - A ridiculously elegant Jekyll theme" /><published>2019-02-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/introducing-reverie-jekyll-theme</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/introducing-reverie-jekyll-theme/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amitmerchant1990/reverie&quot;&gt;Reverie&lt;/a&gt; is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;-powered theme which is simple and opinionated. It’s actually a fork of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/barryclark/jekyll-now&quot;&gt;jekyll-now&lt;/a&gt; with some additional features and personal touches which I’ve implemented to suit my needs for my blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a plug-and-play Jekyll theme which you can use on GitHub Pages without even setting up a local environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/reverie-demo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features-overview&quot;&gt;Features overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Command-line free fork-first workflow, using GitHub.com to create, customize and post to your blog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fully responsive and mobile optimized base theme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sass/Coffeescript support using Jekyll 2.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free hosting on your GitHub Pages user site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All the SEO goodies comes in-built&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Markdown blogging&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Syntax highlighting using Pygments
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://draculatheme.com/&quot;&gt;Dracula syntax theme&lt;/a&gt; included&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disqus commenting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google Analytics integration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fuzzy search across blog posts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pagination of posts works out-of-the-box.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Categorize posts out-of-the box&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RSS Feed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In-built sitemap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
 &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//cdn.carbonads.com/carbon.js?serve=CE7D6KJY&amp;amp;placement=wwwamitmerchantcom&quot; id=&quot;_carbonads_js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-reverie-on-github-pages&quot;&gt;Using Reverie on GitHub Pages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1-fork-reverie-to-your-user-repository&quot;&gt;Step 1) Fork Reverie to your User Repository&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fork &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amitmerchant1990/reverie&quot;&gt;this repository&lt;/a&gt;, then rename the repository to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;yourgithubusername.github.io&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amitmerchant1990/reverie/generate&quot;&gt;Use this template&lt;/a&gt; button if you want to create a repository with a clean commit history which will use Reverie as a template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your Jekyll blog will often be viewable immediately at &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourgithubusername.github.io&quot;&gt;https://yourgithubusername.github.io&lt;/a&gt; (if it’s not, you can often force it to build by completing step 2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2-customize-and-view-your-site&quot;&gt;Step 2) Customize and view your site&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter your site name, description, avatar and many other options by editing the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file. You can easily turn on Google Analytics tracking, Disqus commenting and social icons here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a change to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_config.yml&lt;/code&gt; (or any file in your repository) will force GitHub Pages to rebuild your site with jekyll. Your rebuilt site will be viewable a few seconds later at &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourgithubusername.github.io&quot;&gt;https://yourgithubusername.github.io&lt;/a&gt; - if not, give it ten minutes as GitHub suggests and it’ll appear soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3-publish-your-first-blog-post&quot;&gt;Step 3) Publish your first blog post&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a new file called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/_posts/2019-2-13-Hello-World.md&lt;/code&gt; to publish your first blog post. That’s all you need to do to publish your first blog post! This &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/wiki/Markdown-Cheatsheet&quot;&gt;Markdown Cheatsheet&lt;/a&gt; might come in handy while writing the posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You can add additional posts in the browser on GitHub.com too! Just hit the &lt;kbd&gt;Create new file&lt;/kbd&gt; button in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/_posts/&lt;/code&gt; to create new content. Just make sure to include the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/frontmatter/&quot;&gt;front-matter&lt;/a&gt; block at the top of each new blog post and make sure the post’s filename is in this format: year-month-day-title.md&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-categories-in-reverie&quot;&gt;Using Categories in Reverie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can categorize your content based on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;categories&lt;/code&gt; in Reverie. For this, you just need to add &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;categories&lt;/code&gt; in front matter like below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For adding single category:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-md highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;categories: JavaScript
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For adding multiple categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-md highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;categories: &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;PHP, Laravel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contegorized content can be shown over this URL: &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourgithubusername.github.io/categories/&quot;&gt;https://yourgithubusername.github.io/categories/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rss&quot;&gt;RSS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generated &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS&quot;&gt;RSS feed&lt;/a&gt; of your blog can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourgithubusername.github.io/feed&quot;&gt;https://yourgithubusername.github.io/feed&lt;/a&gt;. You can see the example RSS feed over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amitmerchant.com/reverie/feed&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sitemap&quot;&gt;Sitemap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generated sitemap of your blog can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://yourgithubusername.github.io/sitemap&quot;&gt;https://yourgithubusername.github.io/sitemap&lt;/a&gt;. You can see the example sitemap feed over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amitmerchant.com/reverie/sitemap&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;license&quot;&gt;License&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MIT&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">Reverie is a Jekyll-powered theme which is simple and opinionated. It’s actually a fork of jekyll-now with some additional features and personal touches which I’ve implemented to suit my needs for my blog.</summary></entry></feed>