<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-10T17:40:44+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Queer Tools</title><subtitle>Notes Toward a Dissertation</subtitle><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><entry><title type="html">Zooming out of Chapter One</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/zooming-out-of-chapter-one/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zooming out of Chapter One" /><published>2020-07-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/zooming-out-of-chapter-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/zooming-out-of-chapter-one/">&lt;p&gt;About a week ago I converted my chapter document into a word
doc. Until now, I’ve only been engaging with the draft on through the
text editor Emacs using Org Mode, an amazing format that allows you to
collapse paragraphs and outlines to make writing cleaner and more
navigable. As a result, however, I didn’t have a sense of how long my
document was until I opened it in Word. Turns out I have 34 pages
single spaced. And I still need to draft what I think will take up
about one third of the chapter. Clearly, some revision and
reorganization is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I took the week to go through the entire doc, writing concise
notes and outlines of my work so far, and flagging things that still
need to be done. Below is an image of the first 2/3 or so of the
chapter draft, showing the outline and flags for specific sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/org_outline.png&quot; alt=&quot;image of chapter outline in emacs org
mode&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After taking this time to step back and see the big picture, I feel a
lot better about the work that I’ve already achieved, though almost
all of the paragraphs need some work in revising and refining. There’s
still a long way to go, but there’s also an arc here, a form of my
argument that takes shape despite the gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I’m going to set some goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;first, the next week (July 27) I will draft the final third of the
chapter. This will be hard work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the next two weeks, (august 3 &amp;amp; 10) will be spent on cleaning up the
first three sections, “intro to touch” and “queerness as untouchable,”
and “solutions.” This is to prepare for sharing those pages with my
Undercommons writing group in mid-August.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;then, starting August 17 until September, I’ll revise the rest of
the chapter, fulfilling any lingering TODOs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;following this schedule, by the end of August I will hopefully have
something, even if not perfect, to send to Matt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I revise, I find myself more and more myred in the various
definitions of queerness. It will be important to keep the following
in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being queer is, at its core, a desire for connection—with oneself
or with others—that is continually thwarted by the oppression,
categories, and heteronormativity of dominant culture. Queerness which
we can only engage within formalized or opaque structures—the formal
experiments of queer writers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The “untouchable” denotes a state of &lt;em&gt;suspended knowledge&lt;/em&gt; (about queer
subjectivity and experience) that allows me to then turn to &lt;em&gt;feeling
and affect&lt;/em&gt; as epistemological methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">About a week ago I converted my chapter document into a word doc. Until now, I’ve only been engaging with the draft on through the text editor Emacs using Org Mode, an amazing format that allows you to collapse paragraphs and outlines to make writing cleaner and more navigable. As a result, however, I didn’t have a sense of how long my document was until I opened it in Word. Turns out I have 34 pages single spaced. And I still need to draft what I think will take up about one third of the chapter. Clearly, some revision and reorganization is necessary.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Drafting the Intro</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/close-reading-intro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Drafting the Intro" /><published>2020-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/close-reading-intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/close-reading-intro/">&lt;p&gt;My past two posts have been clarifying the concept of “untouchable”
and how it functions in relation to queerness. “Untouchable” denotes a
state of &lt;em&gt;suspended knowledge&lt;/em&gt; (about queer subjectivity and
experience) that allows me to then turn to &lt;em&gt;feeling and affect&lt;/em&gt; as
epistemological methods.
    - First, I worked out a definition of “untouchable” as the raw
      data about queer subjectivity and experience that cannot be
      quantified. (later in the chapter, I will explain that in order
      to engage (or “interface”) with this data, we need abstraction
      and formalization.
	- Then, I looked for analogies of the “untouchable” in other
      fields (history and science) that display the impulse to verify,
      correct, or recover. In literary studies, this impulse for
      satisfaction is observed in “paranoid” or “suspicious” reading
      practices, which attempt to find “hidden meaning” in texts in a
      way that constrains inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These past two weeks, I’ve been working on the introduction, because
it occurs to me that I need a solid definition of queerness before
moving on to describe how queerness is untouchable. So I defined the
core condition of queerness being &lt;strong&gt;“the desire for touching,” a
desire that is ultimately frustrated, deferred, or eluded&lt;/strong&gt; (analogous
to Jose Munoz’s concept of queer horizon, the state of being “not yet
here”). Being queer is, at its core, a desire for connection—with
oneself or with others—that is continually thwarted by the
oppression, categories, and heteronormativity of dominant culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “desire for touching,” without being able to fully touch, as the
definition of queerness, is also where the digital and queer
intersect. Digital media creates the illusion that we have access to
data, to information, but all we have access to is a &lt;em&gt;formalized&lt;/em&gt;
relationship to that data. We encounter the digital object through
mediation, through an interface, mice, GUIs, keyboards, etc. It is the
same with queernes, which we can only engage within formalized or
opaque structures—the formal experiments of queer writers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m trying to begin the chapter with this meditation on the
intersection of the digital and queerness. Right now, I’m doing so by
providing a few close readings, right at the start, which define
queerness as a thwarted desire for touching. In the example I’ve
chosen, by Jordy Rosenberg’s &lt;em&gt;Confessions of the Fox&lt;/em&gt;, I use an
evocative quote that characterizes sexual desire not on touch, but how
precluding touch activates other sensations that are more physical,
more intense, than touch. Then I jump to a hypertext novella, &lt;em&gt;These
Waves of Girls&lt;/em&gt; by Caitlin Fisher, and discuss how the narrative pull
of clicking through the text enacts a desire for closure or
understanding that is never fully satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It occurs to me now that I need to go a little more into the &lt;em&gt;Waves&lt;/em&gt;
example, include a bit of media archaeology, the formal and forensic
(Matt Kirschenbaum) levels of materiality, and a bit about how
hypertext works, to fully round out this point. I’m drawing a parallel
between what Rosenberg is doing with refusing touch and what Fisher is
doing by frustrating touch. They are both searching for alternative
modes of connections, modes that active a fuller sensorium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the introduction might be structured thus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an opening statement on how touch relates to queerness and the
digital&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a definition of queerness as deferred desire for touching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;introducing two case studies that demonstrate how queerness engages
this idea of deffered touch in text and digital media.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this introduction, which is only meant to pique interest and
 set ideas into motion, I will move on to exploring the “untouchable”
 state of queerness in depth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">My past two posts have been clarifying the concept of “untouchable” and how it functions in relation to queerness. “Untouchable” denotes a state of suspended knowledge (about queer subjectivity and experience) that allows me to then turn to feeling and affect as epistemological methods. - First, I worked out a definition of “untouchable” as the raw data about queer subjectivity and experience that cannot be quantified. (later in the chapter, I will explain that in order to engage (or “interface”) with this data, we need abstraction and formalization. - Then, I looked for analogies of the “untouchable” in other fields (history and science) that display the impulse to verify, correct, or recover. In literary studies, this impulse for satisfaction is observed in “paranoid” or “suspicious” reading practices, which attempt to find “hidden meaning” in texts in a way that constrains inquiry.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Untouchable Queerness</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/the-untouchable/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Untouchable Queerness" /><published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/the-untouchable</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/the-untouchable/">&lt;p&gt;In my last post, I started to organize my thoughts on feminist distant
reading. My focus was to work out how we might open up the way we
interface with queerness as “untouchable,” as the raw data that cannot
be quantified. The solution is to abstract and formalize so we can
move or “interface” with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past few weeks I have dived into the issue of the
“untouchable”—what does it mean for the way we do critique?
Primarily, I’ve been looking for ways that other fields have eschewed
the impulse to verify, correct, or recover. In what follows, I outline
the main argument from the first third of my chapter, where I lay out
the state of queerness as “untouchable” by finding analogies in the
fields of science and history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, queerness is defined as a desire for touch (the digital), a
desire that cannot be satisfied, redeemed, or recovered. This impulse
for satisfaction is observed in “paranoid” or “suspicious” reading
practices, which seek to answer or discover the “hidden” meaning in
text. These practices attempt to answer questions, but do so in a way
that constrains inquiry. This is because paranoia only delivers the
results that are /imaginable/ within current the knowledge
structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see the harm of paranoia, for example, in methods of science and
histor. We encounter excellent critiques of these methods particularly
in recovery projects, such as slave history or the black
atlantic. Here, the goal of recovery creates a system of inquiry that
predetermines the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is related to queerness, which is untouchable. It is a feeling of
embodied disembodiment, estrangement, loss. The state of queerness is
incommensurable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The burden of my writing in this section is to draw the ties between
racial critique and queer, in a way that doesn’t diminish or
wrongfully appropriate the POC scholarship. I’m not trying to suggest
an equivalence, but pointing out that this kind of work has already
been done in other contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section sets up the last part of the chapter, where I’ll discuss
the preferred method of speculation, drawing from speculative history
methods by Saidiya Hartman, Lisa Lowe, and David Kazanjian, among
others such as Gloria Anzaldua and Cherrie Moraga. The harm of
paranoia comes from the subject/object divide, where the dominant
subject takes control/power over the other. Looking to work done in
slave history recovery, in chicanx studies and literature, we find
alternative ways of reading that involve speculation and play. They
require formalizing and abstracting what cannot be touched into a
touchable format. It involves playing with vantages (Lauren Klein),
provisionality (Julia Flanders, Susan Brown), and performance
(Katherine Bode, Tanya Clement).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">In my last post, I started to organize my thoughts on feminist distant reading. My focus was to work out how we might open up the way we interface with queerness as “untouchable,” as the raw data that cannot be quantified. The solution is to abstract and formalize so we can move or “interface” with it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Feminist Army II</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/feminist-army-II/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feminist Army II" /><published>2020-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/feminist-army-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/feminist-army-II/">&lt;p&gt;It’s been difficult to stay focused during the pandemic. Only the past
week have I been able to return to my dissertation work, and just to
go over my reading notes taken in the weeks prior to march 16, when I
left New York. I was working through a mountain of reading and
research in response to a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Caladoscope/status/1232711183288934400&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; I
sent out about a month ago asking for examples of
non-white-cis-male-het distant reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after this time of research and note-taking, I feel ready to start
writing again, and I’m starting to constellate some of the central
findings in the work of great feminist scholarship on distant
reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my last post, I zeroed in on what I see as the crux of my chapter’s
argument, where I think much of this research will be deployed. The
chapter starts off with this conundrum—pointing out the necessity of
touch, and then the reality of queer experience and “raw data” which
are untouchable, sharing in the status of being constructed in some
way. The answer to handling this construction is to celebrate the
necessity of critical detachment and how it opens up the way we
interface with constructions. By abstracting data we can move with
them and find new modes of moving with with them. The method lies in
bodies “touching” through their own abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my reading, I found that much of the writers were inspired by
Drucker, or build off Drucker’s ideas as foundational to their
thinking. There is this general agreement that all data is capta. They
build off this notion into different directions, and below are the two
strands I find most useful for my project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the first is the strand of &lt;em&gt;criticism as performance&lt;/em&gt;. Critics like
Katherine Bode and Tanya Clement stress the performativity of the
critical process; Bode emphasizing more the materiality of the
critical apparatus, and Clement emphasizing the process of
discovery. Both are heavily indebted to ideas from textual
criticism, particularly of Jerome McGann. They are formalists.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the second strand is of &lt;em&gt;dynamicity&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;vantages&lt;/em&gt;. These critics
look at how computation affords possibilities for social critique by
refusing “totalizing” narratives and approaching modeling as
something partial yet dynamic. Lauren Klein looks for methods that
engage multiple dimensions of the invisible in data; Laura Mandell
at how we might “animate numerical processes” rather than establish
them; and Susan Brown’s category work exhorts critics to work with
provisionality, rather than aim for permanence. I could also add
Julia Flanders and Pamela Caughie to this list.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does it make sense for me to separate these two strands? They are both
based on approaching criticism as a vital exercise, but they seem to
differ on the emphasis of social vs formal critique. Is that a
separation I want to uphold here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’m really interested is in how these critics address the body in
their processes. How can I incorporate a concern for affect here?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">It’s been difficult to stay focused during the pandemic. Only the past week have I been able to return to my dissertation work, and just to go over my reading notes taken in the weeks prior to march 16, when I left New York. I was working through a mountain of reading and research in response to a tweet I sent out about a month ago asking for examples of non-white-cis-male-het distant reading.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Feminist Army</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/feminist-army/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feminist Army" /><published>2020-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/feminist-army</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/feminist-army/">&lt;p&gt;Over the past two weeks, I continue to interweave discussions on queer
theory and dh methods, focusing on what they share—the sensitivity
to textual objects, mediated by the critic’s self-consciousness of her
distance from the object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been difficult to keep a structure, and I continue to revise my
outlines as I add more theorists. So far, I’ve come up with this
master sketch for the chapter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;touch as a reading method: making &amp;amp; opening connections
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;anzaldua and sedgwick on touch as connective and multiplying&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;queerness as untouchable: something we cannot fully grasp
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;love and cvetkovitch on queer negativity&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;data as unknowable: something we cannot fully grasp
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;drucker and underwood on studying cooked data&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the illusion of critical detachment, we need bodies
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;felski’s affective method&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;sedgwick on reparative reading&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;abstraction as necessary in order to bring things into relation
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;sedgwick on generative shame&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;klein on figuring what is absent&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the parallels between DH and Queer theorists, different reading
styles; refocus on touch
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;feminist distant reading&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;mcgann, ramsay on deformance, piper on close &amp;amp; distant.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;example of queer theorist who is guided by
touching/feeling… affect theories? Munoz, Anzaldua, Ahmed…&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my reading of /voyant-tools/ &amp;amp; /waves/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The progression builds off the notion of touch, then immediately
brings in that which is untouchable—queerness and data, and starts
to plot how we might move from there, into a criticism that celebrates
detachment by turning to the body and abstraction. Bodies engaging
with the subject matter through abstraction. By abstracting data, we
can move within them and interface with them. Something along those
lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writing process is slow, as I’m trying to coordinate my readings
of the critics and bring them into a narrative. There are moments,
however, when I break free from my critics, to articulate without
substantiation the focus on touch and the necessity of critical
distance. In those moments the writing is loose and easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I’m trying very deliberately to base my method on work
done by women and especially queer women of color. When it comes to
digital humanities, this has been tough, because as Sara Ahmed says,
whiteness and maleness automatically reproduce themselves. We
reproduce them without intention, and it takes a willful effort to
center other voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that vein, I tweeted out a call for “non-cishet-white-male distant
reading.” The responses I got were overwhelming, with people citing
their own work and others. So I’m inundated with some exciting reading
for the next couple of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">Over the past two weeks, I continue to interweave discussions on queer theory and dh methods, focusing on what they share—the sensitivity to textual objects, mediated by the critic’s self-consciousness of her distance from the object.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Queerness as Data</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/queer-data/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Queerness as Data" /><published>2020-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/queer-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/queer-data/">&lt;p&gt;So I’ve been taking the first stabs at the dissertation, trying to get
down a draft of the foundational chapter, which is about methods. The
goal is to weave together reading methods from specific strands of
Queer Theory and the Digital Humanities, trying to fixate on what they
share, which is a sensitivity to the critic’s distance from the
textual subject, a relationality. I’m trying to map out this
parallelism about the way that these theorists treat the objects of
their study—as incapable of being fully figured—and the moment of
convergence, which is the act of identification, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Queer Theory side, I’ve started with Heather Love’s &lt;em&gt;Feeling
Backward&lt;/em&gt;, drawing out Love’s descriptions of queer subjects as
unredeemable and lost in their own sufffering. She is largely
responding to critical narratives that try to resolve or recuperate
the psychic trauma undergone by queer subjects, transforming them into
pride, liberation, or at least the acknowledgment of repression. She
argues against an “affirmative” reading of these subjects, insisting
instead that critics allow them their ambiguity and use that as a
foundation for theorizing. For example, she reads in Walter Pater a
hesitance, a preference to linger in a space of withdrawal, before the
emergence of modern homosexual identity, in “a world in which time was
suspended” (58). Her reading materializes the “dual movement of
solicitation and self-effacement” (59) in his writing, and theorizes
what she calls “the epistemology of the vestibule” (64) into a
politics of suspension and inaction. For Love, the experience of
queerness cannot be captured, it is something raw and elusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Love’s “feeling backward,” I turn to an example from DH about
analytical methods that cannot fully capture the complexity of
data. Johanna Drucker’s “Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display”
explains how all data, rather than “given,” is actually “taken” or
constructed, what she calls &lt;em&gt;capta&lt;/em&gt;. Drucker goes into detail about
how quantification necessarily reduces and eliminates many aspects
about itself, obscuring its own interpretive choices. She gives the
example of a graph which shows number of books published by year, and
points out that such a graph hides the reason for choosing
“publication date” as a measure of productivity, rather than, for
instance, composition, editing, review, distribution, etc. For
Drucker, all visualizations, in simplifying and regularizing their
data, collapse certain aspects about their subjects in ways that mask
their actual constructedness. To counter this misrepresentation,
Drucker deliberately messes with graphical metrics, breaking lines and
blurring bars, showing how the entities of data are actually fuzzy,
malleable, and above all, unknowable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between Drucker and Love, I try to bring out the way they similarly
approach the objects of their study as somehow beyond the critic’s
grasp. Drucker makes evident what is overlooked or assumed when
dealing with complex subjects. She places those elements there, for
all to see, in a way that muddles the relationship between them. Like
Love, Drucker works on the “image of exile, of refusal, even of
failure” (Love 71).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step for me is to hone this idea of identification. In my
section on Love, I spend some time proposing identification as a
reading method. By “identification,” I mean the act in which the
critic finds something in the textual subject that touches or
&lt;em&gt;coincides&lt;/em&gt; with the critic. In what ways does this act of
“identification” also relate to the ways we respond to graphical or
quantified information? Can we “identify” with a graphic? I’m not sure
this is the route to go. I think I need to reframe identification as a
means of feeling, of being pulled forward. What pulls the reader
through a queer narrative, similarly to what pulls the user through a
graphical interface. It is a motive force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some other things that came up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Throughout my discussion of Drucker, I’m trying to respond to
Moretti (presenting him in direct opposition to many of her ideas)
without naming him explicitly in the body of my writing. Instead, I’m
relegating him to the footnotes, an appendage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ve also been reading Yiyun Li’s &lt;em&gt;Dear Friend, from my Life I Write
to you in your Life&lt;/em&gt;, which is clarifying the way that I think about
the confines of identification. Li very clearly presents a paradigm
for reading &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to identify (she doesn’t see herself in ficitonal
characters) but to acquire a certain invisibility among others. Need
to think more about this need to be with but not of the subjects that
we read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">So I’ve been taking the first stabs at the dissertation, trying to get down a draft of the foundational chapter, which is about methods. The goal is to weave together reading methods from specific strands of Queer Theory and the Digital Humanities, trying to fixate on what they share, which is a sensitivity to the critic’s distance from the textual subject, a relationality. I’m trying to map out this parallelism about the way that these theorists treat the objects of their study—as incapable of being fully figured—and the moment of convergence, which is the act of identification, I think.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Application Week</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/application-week/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Application Week" /><published>2020-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/application-week</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/application-week/">&lt;p&gt;This week I’ve been writing fellowship &amp;amp; grant applications and paper
proposals. I’ve applied to two places (the DSRG and the Clark) to get
money to go to LA and see the Wilde typescript. Besides these
applications, I also submitted an abstract to a special edition of
Digital Humanities Quarterly on Minimal Computing, on my highlighter
tool as a tool that resists the tendency of EdTech to track and
quantify student data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing out the various proposals forced me to see my project within
the space of few sentences, and I struggled here to articulate the
role of “queerness.” Here’s what I came up with in the intro:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Within the broad field of the Digital Humanities (DH), an emerging
Queer DH explores what is queer about digital methods and media. These
initiatives often critique the practice of using digital tools to
verify, correct, or establish “facts” about cultural materials,
preferring instead to orient technological contexts around speculation
and experimentation. In support of such efforts, my project excavates
the limitations of digital methods that overlook or collapse the
complexity of literary materials to consider how they might open
possibilities for queer scholarship. I examine how the processes of
electronic editing, social reading and archiving tools draw attention
to the ambiguities of queer subjectivity, experience, and
embodiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main point I was trying to get across is how “queerness” in media
centers on the ways that tools act unexpectedly, give us unexpected or
suprising results—they are “queer” in sense that they diverge from
the “norm”. This idiosyncrasy (and it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an idiosyncrasy) of digital
tools results from the condition of being embodied, of their material
and physical existence as hardware and software, a condition that’s
often overlooked by what Matt Kirschenbaum calls digital media’s
“formal materiality,” the illusion that objects on the screen have no
connection to hardware realities. So, in order to explore this
condition, it’s necessary to take apart the machine, to look at its
components and software to see how it works. We start to see how
machines are not the flawless, homogenous, objective workers we
thought them to be, we see how they are built by humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we begin to look more closely into computational processes, we also
see the parallels between computational and human cognitive
processing. We start to appreciate how both humans and machines
closely resemble each other, how they both make mistakes and
misreadings. We start to develop a new way of understanding how they
might interact, how they can fit (or mis/fit) together. This is where
queer materiality leads to dis/ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a strange trajectory of ideas here: first I’m saying that there’s
something flawed and messed up about computers, something
fundamentally physical and therefore unpredictable. Then I’m saying
this problem with computers actually reflects the way that humans are
built, the way that human bodies, perception, memory works. &lt;em&gt;Then&lt;/em&gt; I’m
saying that this creates new ways of looking at human/computer
interactions. This new way accepts difference, surprise,
strangeness—queerness—as a minimum for interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to me a very tenuous line of argument, something that can
be easily critiqued and taken down at each step. Especially when
considering the other ways I use queer, which is a reading practice
and a subject matter. Maybe those other understanding of queer build
toward this one about media and bodies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thought—more exciting—that my dissertation chapters can
focus on one part of the above argument:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;first chapter: on reading—there is something fundamentally
physical and therefore unpredictable about computational
processes. Creates a critical distance /relationality between reader
and text.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;second chapter: on editing—this issue with computers actually
reflects back to a human issue (Caughie: the questioning of
computing gender leads us back to gender ontology) of fully knowing
and formalizing ourselves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;third chapter: on annotating—this queerness shared across humans
and computers can guide the way we create/use digital tools, in a
way that accepts difference, surprise, strangeness as a minimum for
interaction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fourth chapter: archiving—do I need a fourth chapter? Maybe this
can become some kind of epilogue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">This week I’ve been writing fellowship &amp;amp; grant applications and paper proposals. I’ve applied to two places (the DSRG and the Clark) to get money to go to LA and see the Wilde typescript. Besides these applications, I also submitted an abstract to a special edition of Digital Humanities Quarterly on Minimal Computing, on my highlighter tool as a tool that resists the tendency of EdTech to track and quantify student data.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections from GC-DRI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/digital-research-institute/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections from GC-DRI" /><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/digital-research-institute</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/digital-research-institute/">&lt;p&gt;The past few days we have been running our annual &lt;a href=&quot;https://gcdri.commons.gc.cuny.edu/&quot;&gt;Digital Research
Institute&lt;/a&gt; at the Graduate Center
Digital Initiatives. I’ve taught three sessions of python, and
supported sessions on Text Analysis, as well as helping out in Command
Line, Git/Github, and attended Mapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’ve found, or realized once again, is how much my approach
toward data and method informs my interest in DH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I watched the Text Analysis workshop unfold, the most striking
realization was the preconceptions and biases we bring into our
inferences. We might make certain assumptions about analysis. For
example, in Natural Language Toolkit’s (NLTK) &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;similar()&lt;/code&gt; method, we
measure what words are similar to any other word. In the analysis
below, we see what words are associated to “love” across two different
texts, &lt;em&gt;Moby Dick&lt;/em&gt; (text1) and &lt;em&gt;Sense And Sensibility&lt;/em&gt; (text2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/love-similar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finding words that are similar to &amp;quot;love&amp;quot; in *Moby Dick* and *Sense
and Sensibility*&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Melville, love is associated with the strong natural forces,
having to do with nature (“sea,” “whale,” “fear”) and men, male bodies
(“head,” “hand,” “him,” “me”). In Austen, the word love has
associations with domestic life, family and specific people (“sister,”
“mother,” “elinor,” “marianne”). Both Melville and Austen share “head”
and “him,” though Austen also has “heart” (while Melvill has “hand”)
and “her.” In Austen, affect is associated with “affection,” while
Melville associates it with “fear.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder how our analysis might change when we know the text is
written by a woman. What kinds of conclusions are we tempted to draw?
Presumably, that love for Austen is associated with familial
affection, and for Melville, with awe of nature and man, and that
these differences indicate gender differences. To be overly reductive:
women find love in the home, and men out in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this desire to draw conclusions isn’t the right approach, or at
least it’s not the most interesting to me. I am not doing text
analysis to answer a question. I am doing it to arrive at the
question, which is a way to keep the literary conversation going (see
Stephen Ramsay, &lt;em&gt;Algorithmic Criticism&lt;/em&gt;). During the session, Rafa
said something that reinforced this idea, that “text analysis is just
playing with lists.”  That idea of play is the space I want to stay
in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of play, I’m thinking a lot about how we can try to
queer or mess around with some of the reductions of “cleaning text.”
Obviously, the more and more you clean your data, that you simplify
and regularize strings, the easier it is to see the relationships
between them (Moretti: “where &lt;em&gt;distance&lt;/em&gt; is a condition of
&lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt;”). Lemmatizing words, stemming them, removing stopwords
and punctuation, are ways of reducing the complexity of data in order
to make comparisons between them and draw conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m proposing that we take a closer look at some of the data that
is often ignored in text analysis, which are “stopwords.” Stopwords
are text that are commonly used and thought to be semantically void,
such as articles and prepositions. I compiled a list of stopwords from
one of my favorite texts,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks02/0200331.txt&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Orlando: A Biography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Virginia
Woolf:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;['for', 'there', 'be', 'no', 'of', 'his', 'the', 'of', 'the',
'did', 'to', 'it', 'was', 'in', 'the', 'of', 'at', 'the', 'of', 'a',
'which', 'from', 'the', 'was', 'the', 'of', 'an', 'and', 'more', 'or',
'the', 'of', 'for', 'the', 'and', 'a', 'or', 'of', 'the', 'on', 'a',
'or', 'his', 'had', 'it', 'from', 'the', 'of', 'a', 'who', 'had',
'up', 'under', 'the', 'in', 'the', 'of', 'and', 'now', 'it', 'in',
'the', 'which', 'through', 'the', 'of', 'the', 'of', 'the', 'who',
'had', 'him', 'had', 'in', 'of', 'and', 'and', 'by', 'and', 'they',
'had', 'of', 'off', 'and', 'them', 'to', 'from', 'the', 'too', 'he',
'he', 'was', 'only', 'and', 'too', 'to', 'with', 'them', 'in', 'or']
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who is familiar with &lt;em&gt;Orlando&lt;/em&gt; will notice the cadence of the
first few sentences in these lines. I’m interested in how these words,
often overlooked, can give us some insight into the movement of the
text. Can prepositions help to suggest the energy or tone of a passage?
How might they be compared to what William James describes in “Stream
of Thought” as the the “moments of flight” between “images” or “resting places”
(typically conveyed by nouns and adjectives)? I don’t know if this
line of thinking will lead anywhere, but it seems like an interesting
project.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">The past few days we have been running our annual Digital Research Institute at the Graduate Center Digital Initiatives. I’ve taught three sessions of python, and supported sessions on Text Analysis, as well as helping out in Command Line, Git/Github, and attended Mapping.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">M– asks me some questions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/m-questions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="M-- asks me some questions" /><published>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/m-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/m-questions/">&lt;p&gt;Submitted my prospectus to the English office today. It’s been a long
process—three months, three drafts, two reviews in Dissertation
Workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I changed the introduction, going more directly into Queer DH. I also
narrowed down the focus of the main paragraphs after the intro:
reading method, Life Writing, Cyborgs, and added a paragraph on
“Queer,” used in three ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Queer Methods (reading practices, relationality—touching but not
touching)- A reading method, searching for moments of misfitting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Queer Materiality (queer subjects, digital media)- At the level of
the body and the computer, looking at the materiality of “mind” and
“computation”. Close reading the man and the machine. A rubric for
engagement, human-machine interactions, the cyborg.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Queer Texts (life writing: memoir &amp;amp; journals, manuscripts)- Formal
experiments of literature that engage experience and cognition as
embodied processes, modes of perception that are
enworlded. Figurations of the digital.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also added a paragraph, “Toward Disability,” which elaborates the
aesthetic encounter between reader and object, the logical conclusion
of a queer relationality, my reading method. Here, I concretize my
interest in “electronic editing schemas that mark elusive
subjectivities, digital annotation tools that visualize affective
responses to reading, and archival digitization efforts that animate
the past.” I also added a paragraph introducting the chapter
descriptions and tying together the threads around this central
question: “How do our current digital tools facilitate queer
encounters with literature?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a meeting last week, M– asked me some questions that helped me to
whittle down my motives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would I summarize my project in one sentence?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About looking at ways that technology disrupts our expectations. How
it prompts the incommensurable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What am I most interested in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The materiality of media, and of human bodies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">Submitted my prospectus to the English office today. It’s been a long process—three months, three drafts, two reviews in Dissertation Workshop.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Certificate Accomplished</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/qt/submitted-itp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Certificate Accomplished" /><published>2019-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/qt/submitted-itp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/qt/submitted-itp/">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I submitted my final paper for the ITP (Interactive
Technology and Pedagogy) certificate program. I started working on
this project in the spring of 2018, when I theorized the purpose of
building and using a (digital) multi-color highlighter to teach
close-reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, I’ve built the highlighter (see my detailed &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gofilipa/digital_annotation/blob/master/notes/development_notes.md&quot;&gt;development
notes&lt;/a&gt;)
and spent a lot more time thinking and writing about how color and
nonverbal methods can help teach critical reading and writing. I’ve
been interested in critiquing Educational Technology (EdTech) tools,
which track and quantify student performance in ways that automate and
standardize learning. I wonder how we can build tools that refuse to
follow these trends of data collection. In the paper, I use the
multi-color highlighter to bring edtech into conversation with
neuroscience, exploring how digital annotation engages embodied
reading practices that subvert edtech’s attempts to measure and
quantify student reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper, as it stands, has some work to do. First, I need to tie
these threads of EdTech and neuroscience more firmly together. I also
need to smooth out the interweaving of my tool’s development (linked
above) to the body of the paper. The goal with inserting the dev notes
throughout the paper is to make my coding work more visible, signaling
to the nontechnical reader some of the confusions and suspensions of
knowledge necessary for this kind of labor, that occur regardless of
technical proficiency. That’s a lot of work to do already, but the
most important task is to finally use this tool in a classroom,
allowing my students to play around with it and inspire further
developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the big obstacle. I cannot use the tool in a classroom until I
get some kind of server authentication for storing and retrieving
annotations. I had a meeting last week with the Hypothes.is
team, and they cannot support the data model of multi-color
annotations, which is understandable. I’m meeting with another of
their developers next week, individually, and I think he can help me
at least to understand the server-side of things so I can potentially
make my own database to store annotations. We will see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more I think about this, however, the more I wish that I had
chosen something less complicated than Hypothes.is to work with. This
tool is much too complex for my purposes, as I’m not interested in
tagging, or even commenting at all. I only need &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalfellows.commons.gc.cuny.edu/2019/10/10/toward-the-end-of-a-digital-project-reflections-on-starting-over/&quot;&gt;a minimal
highlighter&lt;/a&gt;,
a bare-bones highlighter. This kind of tool (I think) would
short-circuit the attempts to track and quantify student performance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Filipa Calado</name></author><summary type="html">Yesterday I submitted my final paper for the ITP (Interactive Technology and Pedagogy) certificate program. I started working on this project in the spring of 2018, when I theorized the purpose of building and using a (digital) multi-color highlighter to teach close-reading.</summary></entry></feed>