<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model
href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Picture of Dorian Gray</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published in periodical format in 1890 (DG90) and as print book in 1891 (DG91). Contains pre-published materials in Morgan Manuscript (MS) and Clark Typescript (TS).</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness xml:id="MS">
                  Wilde, Oscar, <emph>The Picture of Dorian Gray</emph> Morgan Library Manuscript
                  <origDate>1889-90</origDate>
                  Pierpont Morgan Library Dept. of Literary and Historical Manuscripts.
                  264 [i.e., 262] leaves.
                  Original version in thirteen chapters as published in Lippincott's Monthly Magazine for July, 1890.
               </witness>
               <witness xml:id="TS">
                  Wilde, Oscar, <emph>The Picture of Dorian Gray</emph> Clark Library Typescript
                  <origDate>1890</origDate>
                  William Andrews Clark Memorial Library - UCLA, Oscar Wilde and his Literary Circle Collection: Manuscripts and Miscellaneous Materials. 
                  Typescript. 231 leaves. Bound in full gray French levant morocco, gilt tooled. Boxed in full gray French levant morocco. Original typescript with corrections and emendations in Wilde's hand. 
               </witness>
               <witness xml:id="DG90">
                  Wilde, Oscar, "The Picture of Dorian Gray, <emph>Lippincott's Monthly Magazine</emph>
                  Lippincott's Monthly Magazine: a Popular Journal of General Literature, Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott and co., v. 46 July-December 1890.
                  100 p.
                  <origDate>1890</origDate>
               </witness>
               <witness xml:id="DG91">
                  Wilde, Oscar. <emph>The Picture of Dorian Gray: a complete novel</emph> Pierpont Morgan Library Dept. of Printed Books
                  London : Ward, Lock, and Co. ; Philadelphia : J. B. Lippincott Company.
                  100 p.
               </witness>
            </listWit>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
      <div type="chapter" n="1">
         <head>Chapter 1</head>
         <p>
            The studio was filled with the rich odour of roses, and when the light summer wind 
            stirred amidst the trees of the garden there came through the open door the heavy 
            scent of the licac, or the more delicate perfume of the 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <add place="above">pink</add>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            flowering thorn.
         </p>
         <p>
            From the corner of the divan of Persian saddle-boys on which he was lying, smoking, as
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del rend="strikethrough">
                        was his custom,
                     </del>
                     <add place="above">
                        usual
                     </add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            innumerable cigarettes, Lord Henry Wotton could just catch the 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <del rend="strikethrough">
                     <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                  </del>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            gleam of the honey-sweet and hony-colored blossoms of the laburnum, that was hanging 
            from the tremulous branches that seemed hardly able to bear th burden of a beauty so 
            flame-like as theirs: and, now and then, the fantastic shadows of birds in flight 
            flitted across the long tussore-silk curtains that were stretched in front of the huge
            window, producing a kind of momentary Japanese effect, and making him think of those 
            pallid jade-faced painters who, in an art that is  seemingly immobile, seek to convey 
            the laws of swiftness and motion. The sudden murmur of the bees shouldering their way 
            through the long unmown grass or circling with monotonous insistance round the 
            black-crocketed spines of  the early 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <add place="above">
                     June
                  </add>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            holly-hocks, seemed to make the stillness 
            more oppressive,
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <del rend="strikethrough">
                     <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                  </del>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            and the dim roar of London was like the bourdon note of
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <add place="above">
                     a distant
                  </add>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            organ.
         </p>
         <p>
            In the center of the room,
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del rend="strikethrough">
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                     <add place="above">
                        clamped to
                     </add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            an upbright easel,
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <add place="above">
                     was standing
                  </add>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            the full-length portrait of a yound man of extraodinary personal beauty, and in front 
            of it, some little distance away, 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <del rend="strikethrough">
                     <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                  </del>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            sat the 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del rend="strikethrough">painter</del>
                     <add place="above">artist himself,</add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            Basil Hallward, whose sudden disappearance some years ago caused
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <add place="above">at the time</add>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            such
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <add place="above">public</add>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            excitement, and
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del rend="strikethrough">
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                     <add place="above">gave rise to so many strange</add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            conjectures.
         </p>
         <p>
            As he looked at the gracious and comely form he had so skillfully mirrored in his art,
            a 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <del>
                     <unclear reason="illegible">delicate</unclear>
                  </del>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            smile of pleasure passed across his face, and seemed about to linger there. But he 
            suddenly  started up, and closing his eyes placed his fingers upon the lids, as though 
            he sought to imprison within his brain some
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del rend="strikethrough">
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        <add place="above">
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </add>
                     </del>
                     <add place="above">curious</add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            dream from which he feared he might awake.
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>"It is your best work, Basil, the best thing you have ever done,"</quote>
            said Lord Henry languidly. 
            <quote>"You must certainly sent it
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">next year</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               to the Grosvenor. The Academy is too large, and too vulgar. The Grosvenor is the only 
               place." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I don't think I will send it will send it any where," 
            </quote>
            he answered, tossing his head back in that odd way that used to make
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                     <add place="above">his friends</add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            laugh at him in Oxford.
            <quote>
               "No: I won't send it anywhere. And yet, you are quite right about it. It is my best
               work."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Lord Henry elevated his eyebrows, and looked at him in amazement through the thin blue 
            wreathes of smoke that curled
            <app>
               <rdg wit="MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                     <add place="above">up in such fanciful whorls</add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            from his heavy opium-tainted cigarette.
            <quote>
               "Not send it anywhere? My dear fellow, why? Have you got any reason? What odd chaps 
               you painters are! You do any thing in the world to gain a reputation. And soon as 
               you have
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>it</del>
                        <add place="above">one</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               you seem to want to throw it away. It is silly of you, for there is only one thing 
               in the world worse than being talked about, and that is not being talked about. A 
               portrait like this would set you far above all the young men in England, and make 
               the old men
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">quite</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               jealous, if old men are 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">even</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               capable of any emotion."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I know you will laugh at me," he replied, "but I really cannot exhibit it. I have 
               put too much of myself into it."
            </quote>
            Lord Henry stretched his long legs out on the divan, and shook with laughter.
            <quote>
               "Yes: I knew you would laugh, but it is quite true, all the same."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Too much of yourself in it! Upon my word,
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">Basil,</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               I didn't know you were so vain, and I really can't see any resemblance between you 
               with your rugged strong face, and your coal-black hair, and this young Adonis, who 
               looks as if he was made of ivory and rose-leaves. Why, my dear Basil, he is a 
               narcissus! And you–well of course you have an intellectual expression, and all that. 
               But Beauty, real Beauty, 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>only begins</del>
                        <add place="above">ends</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               where an intellectual expression begins. Intellect is in itself an exaggeration, and 
               destroys the harmony of any face. The moment one 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               sits down to think, one becomes all nose, or all forehead, or something horrid. Look 
               at the successful men in any
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add>of the</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               learned professions. How perfectly hideous they are! Except of course in the Church. 
               But then in the Church they don't think. A Bishop keeps on saying at the age of eighty 
               what he was told to say when he was a boy of eighteen, and consequently he
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="MS">
                     <add place="above">always</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               looks absolutely delightful. Your mysterious young friend, whose name you have never 
               told me but whose picture really fascinates me, never thinks. I feel quite sure of 
               that. He is a brainless, beautiful thing, who should be always here in winter when 
               we have no flowers to look at, and 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="MS">
                     <add place="above">always here</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               in summer when we want something to chill our intelligences. Don't flatter yourself, 
               Basil. You are not in the least like him." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "You don't understand me, Harry. Of course I am not like him. I know that perfectly 
               well. Indeed I should be sorry to look like him. You shrug your shoulders? I am 
               telling you the truth. There is a fatality about all physical as well as 
               intellectual distinction, the sort of fatality that seems to dog
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add>through history the faltering</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               steps of Kings. It is better not to be different from one's fellows. The ugly and 
               the stupid have the best of it in this world. They can sit quietly, and gape at the 
               play. If they know nothing of victory, they are
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add>at least spared</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               the knowledge of defeat. They live as we all should live, undisturbed, indifferent, 
               and without disquiet. They neither bring ruin upon ohers, nor ever receive it from 
               alien hands. Your rank and wealth, Harry; my brains, such as they are, my fame, 
               whatever it may be worth; Dorian Grey's 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>beauty</del>
                        <add>good looks</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               we will all suffer for what the Gods have given us, suffer terribly."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Dorian Grey? Is that his name?" 
            </quote>
            said Lord Henry, walking across the studio toward Basil Hallward. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Yes: that is his name. I did'nt intend to tell
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="MS">
                     <add place="above">it to</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               you."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "But why not?" 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Oh! I can't explain.
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               When I like people immensely, I 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>cannot</del>
                        <add place="above">never</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>    
               tell their names to any one. It seems like surrendering a part of them. You know how
               I love secrecy. It is the only thing that can make a modern life woderful, or 
               mysterious to us. The commonest thing is delightful if one only hides it. When I 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>dine out</del>
                        <add place="above">leave town</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app> 
               I never tell my people where I am going. If I did, I would lose all my pleasure. It 
               is a silly habit, I daresay, but somehow it
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               seems to bring a great deal of romance into one's life. I suppose you think me 
               awfully foolish about it?" 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Not at all," answered Lord Henry, laying his hand upon his shoulder; "not at all, 
               my dear Basil. You seem to forget that I am married, and the one charm of marriage 
               is that it makes a life of deception absolutely necessary for both parties. I never 
               know 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>
                             <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add place="above">where</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app> 
               my wife is
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               , and my wife never knows
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add place="above">what</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app> 
               I am
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">doing</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               When we meet – we do meet occasionally, when we dine, out
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">together</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               or go down to the Duke's – we tell each other the most absurd stories with the most 
               serious faces. My wife is very good at it, much better in fact than I am. She never 
               gets confused over her dates, and I always do. But when she does find me out, she 
               never makes a row. I sometimes wish she did, but she merely laughts at me." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I hate the way you talk about your married life, Harry," said Basil Hallward, 
               shaking his hand off, and strolling towards the door that led into the garden. "I 
               believe that you are really a very good husband, but that you are thoroughly ashamed 
               of your own virtues. You are an extraordinary fellow. You neve say a moral thing, 
               and you never do a wrong thing. Your cynicism is simply a pose." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Being natural is simply a pose, and the most irritating pose I know,
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>said</del>
                        <add place="above">cried</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               Lord Henry laughing, and the two young men went out into the garden together, and for a 
               time they did not speak. 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>to each other</del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            After a long pause Lord Henry pulled out his watch. 
            <quote>
               "I am afriad I must be going Basil," he 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>said</del>
                        <add place="above">murmured</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               and before I go I insist on you answering me a question I put to you 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add place="above">half an hour</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app> 
               ago."    
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "What is that?" asked Basil Hallward, keeping his eyes fixed on the ground. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "You know quite well." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I do not, Harry." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Well, I will tell you what it is." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
              "Please don't."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I must. I want you to 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>tell</del>
                        <add place="above">explain to</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               me why you won't exhibit Dorian Gray's picture. I want the real reason." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I told you the real reason." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "No: you did not. You said it was because there was too much of yourself it. Now, 
               that is childish." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Harry," said Basil Hallward,
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>taking</del>
                        <del>hold of his hand and</del>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               looking him straight in the face, "Every portrait that is painted with 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>passion</del>
                        <add place="above">feeling</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               is a portrait of the artist, not of the sitter. The sitter is merely the accident, 
               the occasion. It is not he who is revealed by the painter, it is rather the painter 
               who 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add>on the colours of the canvas</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               reveals himself. The reason why I will not exhibit this picture, is that I am afraid 
               that I have shown in it the secret of my own soul." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Lord Henry 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del>hesistated for a moment</del>
                     <add place="above">laughed</add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "And what is that?" he asked. 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>in a low voice</del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I will tell you," said Hallward, and an 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>look</del>
                        <add place="above">expression</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               of 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>pain</del>
                        <add place="above">perplexity</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               came over his face. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>"Don't if you would rather not"</del>
                        <add place="above">"I am all expectation, Basil"</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               murmured his companion, looking at him. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Oh! There is really very little to tell you, Harry," answered the young painter; 
               "and I am afraid you will hardly understand it." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Lord Henry smiled, and leaning down plucked a ping-petalled daisy from the grass, and 
            examined it. 
            <quote>
               "I am quite sure I shall understand 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>you</del>
                        <add place="above">it</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               ," he replied, gazing intently at the little golden white-feathered disk. 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>that has charmed all our poets from Chaucer to Tennyson</del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            The wind shook some blossoms from the trees, and the heavy lilac blooms, with their 
            clustering stars, moved to and fro in the languid air. A 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del>bird</del>
                     <add place="above">grasshopper</add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            began to 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del>sing</del>
                     <add place="above">chirrup</add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            in 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del>a thicket</del>
                     <add place="above">the grass</add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            , and a long thin dragon-fly floated 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del>past</del>
                     <add place="above">by</add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            on its brown gauze wings. Lord Henry felt as if he coul hear Basil Hallward's heart 
            beating, and he 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <mod type="subst">
                     <del>heard his own breath, with a sense almost of fear</del>
                     <add place="above">wondered what was coming.</add>
                  </mod>
               </rdg>
            </app>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Yes: there is very little to tell you," repeated Hallward 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">rather bitterly</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               "and I 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>am afraid</del>
                        <add place="above">daresay</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               you will be disappointed. Two months ago I went to a crush at Lady Brandon's. You 
               know we poor painters have to show ourselves in society from time to time, just to 
               remind the public that we are not savages. With an evening coat and a white tie, 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">as you told me once</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               any body, 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">even a stockbroker,</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               can gain a reputation for being civilized. Well, after I had been in the room about 
               ten minutes, talking to huge over-scented dowagers and tedious academicians, I 
               suddenly 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>felt</del>
                        <add place="above">became conscious</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app> 
               that some one was looking at me. I turned half way round, and saw Dorian Gray for 
               the first time. When our eyes met, I felt that I 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>grew</del>
                        <add place="above">was growing</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               pale. A curious 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add place="above">feeling</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               of terror came over me. I knew that I had 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               come 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>across</del>
                        <add place="above">face to face</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               someone whose mere personality was so fascinating that it would 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>be
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add place="above">absorb</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app> 
               my 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>life</del>
                        <add place="above">nature</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               , my soul, my art itself. I did not want any 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <add place="above">extreme</add>
                        influence 
                        <del>of that kind</del>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               in my life. You know yourself, Harry, how independant I have always been. My father 
               destined me for the army. I insisted on going to Oxford. Then he made me enter my 
               name at the middle temple. Before I had eaten half a dozed dinners I gave up the 
               Bar, and announced my intention of becoming a painter. I have always been my own 
               master; had at least always been so till I met Dorian Gray. Then – but I 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               don't know how to explain it to you. Something seemed to tell me that I was on the 
               verge of 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               a terible crisis in my life. I had a strange feeling that 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>be
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add place="above">fate</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               had in store for me exquisite joys and exquisite sorrows. I knew that if I spoke to 
               him, I would 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>never leave him till either he or I were dead</del>
                        <add place="above">become absolutely devoted to him, and that I ought not to speak to him.</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               I grew afraid, and turned to 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>leave</del>
                        <add place="above">quit</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               the room. It was not conscience 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">that made me do so,</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               it was cowardice. I 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               take no credit to myself for trying to escape." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Conscience and cowardice are really the same things, Basil. Conscience is the 
               trade-name of the firm, that is all." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>am not sure of that
                           <add place="above">Harry</add>
                        </del>
                        <add place="above">don't believe that, Harry</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               However, whatever was my motive, and it may have been pride, for I used to be very 
               proud, I certainly struggled to the door. There of course I stubled against Lady 
               Brandon. 
               <quote>
                  "You are not going to run away so soon, Mr. Hallward?" She screamed out.
               </quote>
               You know her shrill horrid voice?" 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Yes: she is a peacock in every thing but beauty," said Lord Henry, pulling the 
               daisy to bits with his long nervous fingers. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I could not get rid of her. She brought me up to the Royalties, and people with 
               Stars and Garters, and elderly ladies with gigantic tiaras 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">and hooked noses.</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               She spoke of me as her dearest friend. I had only met her once before, but she took 
               it into her head to lionize me. I believe some picture of mine had made a great 
               success at the time, at least had been chattered about in the penny newspapers, 
               which is the nineteenth century 
               app>
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                    <mod type="subst">
                       <del>
                          <gap reason="illegible"></gap> of fame
                       </del>
                       <add place="above">standard of immortality</add>
                    </mod>
                 </rdg>
               </app>
               Suddenly I found myself face to face with the young man whose 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>beauty</del>
                        <add place="above">personality</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               had so 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">strangely</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               stirred me. We were quite close, almost touching. Our eyes met, again. It was mad of 
               me, but I asked Lady Brandon to introduce me to him. Perhaps it was not so mad after 
               all. It was simply inevitable. We would have spoken to each other without any 
               introduction. I am sure of that. Dorian told me so afterwards." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "And how did Lady Brandon describe this wonderful young 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>narcissus</del>
                        <add place="above">man</add>
                        <del></del>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               ? I know she gives in for giving a rapid precis of 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">all</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               her guests. I remember her bringing
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>up to</del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               me up to a most truculent and red-faced old 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>man</del>
                        <add place="above">gentleman</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               covered all over with orders and ribands, and hissing into my ear in a tragic 
               whisper, which must have been perfectly audible to every body in the room, something 
               like 
               <quote>
                  'Sir Humpty Dumpty – you know – Afghan frontier – Russian intelligence: very 
                  successful man – 
                  <app>
                     <rdg wit="#MS">
                        <del>quite inconsolable</del>
                        <del>wants to marry</del>
                     </rdg>
                  </app>
                  wife killed by an elephant – quite inconsolable – wants to marry a 
                  <app>
                     <rdg wit="#MS">
                        <add place="above">beautiful</add>
                     </rdg>
                  </app>
                  American widow 
                  <app>
                     <rdg wit="#MS">
                        <add place="above">every body does now-a-days</add>
                     </rdg>
                  </app>
                  – hates Mr. Gladstone – but very much interested in beetles – ask him about the new 
                  <app>
                     <rdg wit="#MS">
                        <del>
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                     </rdg>
                  </app>
                  military frontier.' 
               </quote>
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               I simply fled. I like to find out people for myself. But poor Lady Brandon treats 
               her guests, exactly as an auctioneer treats his goods. She either explains them 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">entirely</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               away or tells one everything about them 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>that one does not</del>
                        <add place="above">except what one</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               wants to know. But what did she say about Mr. Dorian Gray?" 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Oh, she murmered, 
               <quote>
                  'charming boy – going to be so ruch – mother and I great friends – engaged to be 
                  married to the same man – I mean married on the same day – how very silly of me! 
                  Quite forget what he does – afriad he doesn't do anything – oh, yes plays the 
                  piano – or is it the violin, dear Mr. Gray?'
               </quote>
                We could niether of us help laughing, and we became friends at once." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Laughter is not a bad beginning for for a friendship, and it is the best ending for 
               one," said Lord Henry plucking another daisy. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         
         <p>
            Hallward burried his face 
            <app>
               <rdg wit="#MS">
                  <del>
                     <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                  </del>
               </rdg>
            </app>
            in his hands.
            <quote>
               "You don't understand what friendship is, Harry," he murmured," or what enmity is 
               for that matter. You like every one, 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>which is the same as
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add place="above">that is to say</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               you are indifferent to every one." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "How horridly unjust of you," cried Lord Henry, tiling his hat ack, and looking up 
               at the little clouds that were drifting across the hollowed turquoise of the 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">summer</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               sky, like ravelled skeins of glossy white silk, were drifting across the hollowed 
               turquoise of the summer sky.
            </quote>
            <quote>
               "Yes" horribly unjust of you. I make a great different between people. I choose my 
               friends for their good looks: my acquaintences for their characters: and my enemies 
               for their brains. A man can't be too careful in the choice of his enemies. I have 
               not got one who is a fool. They are all men of some intellectual power, and 
               consequently they all appreciate me. Is that very vain of me? I think it is rather 
               vain." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I should think it was, Harry. But according to your category, I must be merely an 
               acquaintance." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "My dear old Basil, you are much more than an acquaintance…"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "And much less than a friend. A sort of brother, I suppose?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Oh! Brothers! I don't care for brothers. My elder brother won't die, and my 
               younger brothers
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">seem</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               never 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">to</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               do anything else." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Harry!" 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "My dear fellow, I am not quite serious. But I can't help detesting my relations. I 
               suppose it comes from the fact that we can't stand other people having the same 
               faults as ourselves. I quite sympathize with the rage of the 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">English</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app> 
               democracy 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>to English</del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               against what they call the vices of the upper classes. They 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>to think</del>
                        <add place="above">feel</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               that drunkenness, 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <unclear>and</unclear>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               stupidity, 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">and immorality</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               should be their own special property, and that if any one of us makes an ass of 
               himself 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add place="above">we are</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               poaching on their preserves. When poor Southwark got into the Divorce Court, their
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>rage</del>
                        <add place="above">indignation</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               was quite magnificant. And yet I don't suppose that ten per cent of the lower orders 
               live with their own wives." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I don't agree with a single word that you have said, and, what is more, 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">Harry,</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               I don't believe you do either." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Lord Henry 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>pulled his little straw-colored mousatache, and</del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               stroked his pointed 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <unclear>Henry</unclear>
                        <del>
                           <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                        </del>
                        <add place="above">brown</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app> 
               beard, and tapped the toe of his patent-leather boot with a 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <mod type="subst">
                        <del>thick</del>
                        <add place="above">tassled</add>
                     </mod>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               malacca-cane. How English you are, Basil! If one puts forward an idea to a real 
               Englishman – always a rash thing to do – he never dreams of considering whether the 
               idea is right or wrong. the only thing he considers of any important is whether one 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>is sincere or putting it
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               believes it oneself. Now the value of an idea has nothing whatsoever to do with the 
               sincerity of the man who expresses it. Indeed the probabilities are that the more 
               insincere the man is, the more purely intellectual will the idea be, as 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <add place="above">in that case</add>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               it will not be coloured by either his wants, his desires, or his prejudices. 
               However, I don't propose to discuss 
               <app>
                  <rdg wit="#MS">
                     <del>
                        <gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                     </del>
                  </rdg>
               </app>
               politics, sociology, or metaphysics with you. I like persons better than principle. 
               Tell me more about Dorian Gray. How often do you see him?" 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Every day, Harry. I coudln't 
               [—] 
               be 
               [–] 
               [happy] 
               if I didn't 
               [–]
               see him every day. Of course, sometimes it is only for a few minutes, But a few 
               minutes with somebody one worships mean a great deal." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "
               [—] 
               [But] 
               you 
               [don't] 
               really worship him?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I do." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "How extraordinary! I thought you would never care for anything but your painting – 
               your art, I should say. Art souns better, doesn't it?" 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "He is all my art to me now. I sometimes think, Harry, that there are only two eras 
               [of any importance] 
               in the history of 
               [the world] [-earth-], 
               [the first is] 
               the difference of a new medium 
               [in art], 
               and the second is 
               [the] 
               difference of a new personality 
               [for art also.] 
               What the invention of oil-painting was to the Venetians, the 
               [-beauty-] 
               [face] 
               of Antinous was to late Greek sculpture, and the 
               [-beauty-] [face] 
               of Dorian Gray will some day be to me. It is not merely that I paint from him, draw 
               from him, model from him. Of course I have done all that. He has stood as Paris in 
               dainty armour, and as Adonis with huntsman's cloak and polished boar-spear. Crowned 
               with heavy lotus-blossoms he has sat on the prow of Adrian's barge lookinginto the 
               green turbid Nile. He has leaned over the still pool of some Greek woodland, and 
               seen in the water's silent silver the wonder of his own 
               [-face:-] [beauty:] 
               But he is much more to me than that. I won't tell you that I am dissatisfied with 
               what I have done of him, or that his beauty is such that art cannot expres it. There
               is nothing that art cannot express, and I know the work that I have done, since I 
               met Dorian Gray, is [—] good work, is the best work of my life. But in some curious 
               way – I wonder will you understand me – his personality has suggested to me an 
               entirely new manner in art, an entirely new mode of style. I see things differently, 
               I think of them differently. I can now recreate life in a way that was hidden from 
               me before. "A dream of form in days of thought" – who is it 
               [-that-] [who] 
               says that? – I forget; – but it is what Dorian Gray has been to me. The merely 
               visible presence of this 
               [-boy-] [lad,] 
               though 
               [-twenty summer have shown him-] 
               [he is -just- over twenty] 
               [-roses less scarlet than his lips-] 
               his merely visible presence, ah! I wonder can you realize all that that means. 
               Unconsciously he defines for me the lines of a fresh school, a school that is to 
               have in itself all the passion of the [–—] [romanic] spirit, all the perfection of 
               the spirit that is Greek. The harmony of soul and body – how much that is! We in our 
               madness have separated the two, and have invented as a realism that is bestial, an 
               ideality that is void. Harry! Harry! if you only knew what Dorian Gray is 
               [to me!] 
               You remember that landscape of mine, for which Agnew offered me such 
               [—] a [-—] [huge] 
               price, but whcih I would not part with? It is one of the best things I have ever 
               done. And why is it so? Because, while I was painting it, Dorian Gray sat beside me, 
               [-and as he leaned across to look at it, his cheek [-hair-] hair just brushed [-touched my] my cheek [-hand]. The world becomes young to me when I hold his hand, as when I ask him the --- yield --- their ----–—"] 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Basil, this is 
               [–—] [quite wonderful. I must see Dorian Gray] 
               [-not talk--–—with you----------–—his power, you--------–—to make yourself the--–—of—slave! It is worse than wicked, it is silly. I hate Dorian Gray-]" 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Hallward got up from the seat, and walked up and down the garden. 
            [-A curious smile curled his lips. He seemed like a man in a dream-]. 
            After some time he came back.
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               ‘You don’t understand Harry..." he said. "Dorian Gray is merely to me a motive in 
               art. He is never more present in my work, then when no image of him is there. He is 
               simply a suggestion, as I have said, of a new manner. I see him in the curves of 
               certain lines, in the loveliness and subtleties of certain colours. That is all." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Then why won’t you exhibit his 
               [-picture-] [portrait]
               ?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Because I have put into it 
               [all] 
               the 
               [extraordinary] 
               romance of which, 
               [of course,] 
               I have never dared to speak to him. He knows nothing about it, 
               [he will never know anything about it] 
               but the world 
               [-would-] [might] 
               guess it, and 
               [-where there is merely love, they would see something evil, where there is spectacular passion they would suggest something vile-] 
               I will not bear my soul to their shallow 
               [prying] 
               eyes. My heart shall 
               [-not be made their mockery.-] [never be put under their microscope.] 
               There is too much of myself in 
               [—] [the thing,] 
               Harry, too much of myself!"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Poets are not so scrupulous as you are. They know how useful passion is for 
               publication. Now-a-days a broken heart will run to many editions." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I hate them for it. An artist should create beautiful things, but should put 
               nothing of his own life into them. We live in an age which men treat art as if it 
               were meant to be an autobiography. We have lost the abstract sense of beauty. If I 
               live I will show the world what it is, and for that lesson the world shall never see 
               my portrait of Dorian Gray." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I think you are wrong, Basil, but I won't argue with you. It is only the 
               intellectually lost who ever argue. Tell me; is Dorian Gray very fond of you?" 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Hallward considers for a few moments. 
            <quote>
               "He likes me," he answered after a pause; "I know he likes me. Of course I flatter 
               him dreadfully. I find a strange pleasure in saying things to him that I know I 
               [-will-] [shall] 
               be sorry for having said. I give myself away. 
               [-I told him that beauty like his is genius, is higher-[^—] -than genius, as it needs no explanation, and is one of the great facts of the world, like sunlight or spring time, or what ---- the explanation in dark waters of that thin silver shell we call the moon.-] 
               As a rule, he is charming to me, and we walk home together, from the club, arm in 
               arm, or sit in the studio 
               [-— each other-] 
               and talk of a thousand things. Now and then, 
               [-the -----------------–—] 
               [^—] 
               however, he is horribly thoughtless, and seems to take a real delight in giving me 
               pain. Then I feel, Harry, that I have given away my whole soul to someone 
               [-seems to take a real delight in giving me pain. I can quite understand it. I can imagine myself doing it. But not to him, not to him. Once or twice we have been away together, then I have-] 
               [had] [-him all to myself. I am horribly jealous of him, of course. I never let him talk to me of the people he knows. I like to isolate him from the rest of life, and to think that he absolutely belongs to me. He does not, I know. But it gives me pleasure to think that he does. Harry! I have given this [-boy-] [-young man-] my whole –—] 
               [who treats]
               [-------------] 
               it as if it were a flower to put in his coat, a bit of decoration to charm his 
               vanity, an ornament for a summer's day." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Days in summer, Basil, are apt 
               [-wax long.-] [to linger.] 
               Perhaps you will tire ssooner than he will. It is a sbad thing to think of, but 
               there is no doubt that genius lasts llonger than beauty. That accounts ffor the fact 
               that 
               [we all take such pains to overeducate ourselves] [-we are all horribly overeducated-] 
               in the wild struggle for existence, we want to have something that endures, and so 
               we fill our minds with rubbish and facts, in the silly hope of keeping oour place. 
               The thoroughly well-informed mman – that is 
               [the modern ideal.] 
               [-what we all try to be.-] 
               And the mind of the thoroughly wwell-informed man is a dreadful thing. It is like a 
               bric-a-brac shop, all monsters and dust, and eevery thing priced above its proper 
               value. I think you will tire first, all the same. Some day you will look at him, and 
               he will seem to you to be a little out of drawing, oor you won't like his tone of 
               colour, or something. You will bitterly reproach him in your own heart, and 
               seriously think that he has behaved 
               [—] [very badly to] 
               you. The next time he ccalls, you will be perfectly cold aand indifferent. It will 
               be a great pity, for it will alter you. The worst of having a romance is that it 
               makes one so unromantic."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Harry, don't talk like that. 
               [-I am not afriad of things, but I am afraid of words. I cannot understand how 
               it is that no prophecy has ever been fulfilled. None has, I know. And yet it 
               seems to me that to say a thing, is to bring it to pass. Whatever has found expression 
               becomes true, and what has not found expression can never happen. As for genius 
               lasting longer than beauty – it is only the transitory that stirs me. What is 
               permanent is monotonous, and produces no effect. Our senses become dulled by 
               what is always with us.-]. 
               As long as I live, the personality of Dorian Gray will dominate me. 
               [-If it -–—]memory, there will be a magic in it----–—dream it will be more 
               real than reality-] 
               You 
               [-cannot realize-] [can't feel] 
               what I feel. You change too often." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Ah! My dear Basil, that is exactly why I can feel it. Those who are faithful know 
               only the pleasures of love, it is the faithless who know love's tragedie," and Lord 
               Henry struck a light on a dainy silver case, and began to smoke a cigarette with a 
               self-conscious and self-satisfied air, as if he had summed up life in a phrase.
            </quote>
            There was a rustle of chirriping sparrows in the ivy, and the blue cloud-shadows chased 
            themselves across the grass like swallows. How pleasant it was in the garden! And how 
            delightful other people's emotions were! Much more delightful than their ideas, it 
            seemed to him. One's own soul, and the passions of one's friends – those were the 
            fascinating things in life. He thought with pleasure of the tedious luncheon that he 
            had missed by staying so long with Basil Hallward. Had he gone to his aunt's, he would 
            have been quite sure to have met Lord Goodbody there, and the whole conversation would 
            have been about the housing of the poor, and the necessity for model lodging-houses. It
            was charming to have escaped all that! As he thought of his aunt, an idea seemed to 
            strike him. He turned to Hallward, and said 
            <quote>
               "My dear fellow, I have just remembered." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Rememberd what, Harry?" 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Where I heard the name of Dorian Gray." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Where 
               [-I heard the name of-] 
               was it?" Asked Hallward, with a slight frown. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Don't look so angry, Basil. It was at my aunt's, Lady Agatha's. She told me she had 
               discovered a wonderful young man, who was going to help her in the East End, and 
               that his name was Dorian Gray. I am bound to state that she never told me he was 
               good-looking. Women have no appreciation of good looks. At least, good women have 
               not. She saw that he was very earnest, and had a beautiful nature. I at once 
               pictured to myself a creature with spectacles and 
               [-no-] [lank] 
               hair, horribly freckled, and 
               [tramping about on] [-with-] 
               huge feet. I wish I had known it was your friend." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I am glad you didn't, Harry." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Why?" 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I don't want you to meet him." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Mr. Dorian Gray is in the studio, Sir" said the butler coming into the garden. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "You must introduce me now," 
               [-said-] [cried] 
               Lord Henry, laughing. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Basil Hallward turned to the 
            [-servant-] [butler] 
            who stood blinking in the sunlight. 
            <quote>
               "Ask Mr. Gray to wait, Parker; I will be in in a few moments." 
            </quote>
            The man bowed, and went up the walk. 
         </p>
         <p>
            Then he looked at Lord Henry. 
            <quote>
               "Dorian Gray is my dearest friend," he said. "He has a simple and a beautiful 
               nature. Your aunt was quite right in what she said of him. Don't spoil him for me. 
               Don't try to influence him. Your influence would be bad. The world is wide, and has 
               many marvellous people in it. Don't take away from me the one person that makes life 
               [-lovely-] 
               absolutely lovely to me, and that gives me my art whatever wonder or charm it 
               possesses. Mind, Harry, I trust you."
            </quote>
            He spoke very slowly, and the words seemed wrung out of him as almost against his will. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "What nonsense you talk," said Lord Henry smiling, and, taking Hallward by the arm, 
               he almost led him into the house. 
            </quote>
         </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="2">
         <head>Chapter Two</head>
         <p>
            As they entered, they saw Dorian Gray. He was seated at the piano with his back to 
            them, turning over the pages of a volume of Schumann's 
            <emph>Forest Scenes.</emph> 
            <quote>
               You must lend me these, Basil," he cried. 
            </quote>
            <quote>
               "I want to learn them. They are perfectly
               charming."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               That entirely depends
               [on]
               how well you wit today, Dorian."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Oh! I am tired of sitting, and I don't want a life-sized portrait of myself, 
               answered the 
               [-boy,-] [+-young +lad,]
               swinging round on the music-stool, in a willful,
               [----] [almost]
               petulant manner.
            </quote>
            When he caught sight of Lord Henry, a faint blush stained his cheeks for a moment, and
            he started up.
            <quote>
               I beg your pardon, Basil, but I didn't know you had anyone with you."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "This is Lord Henry Wotton, Dorian, an old Oxford friend of mine. I have just been
               telling him what a capital sitter you were, and now you have spoiled everything."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "you have not spoiled my pleasure in meeting you, Mr. Gray," said Lord Henry,
               stepping forward and shaking him by the hand. "My aunt has often spoken to me about 
               you. you are one of her favourites, and, I am afraid, one of her victims."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I am in Lady Agatha's black books at present," answered Dorian with a funny look of 
               penitance. "I promised to go to Whitechapel with her last Tuesday, and I really 
               forgot all about it. We were to have played a duet together, three duets I believe.
               I don't know what she will say to me. I am far too frightened to call."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Oh! I will make
               [-my] [+your]
               peace
               [-for you]
               with my aunt. She is quite devoted to you. And I don't think it really matters about
               [-the duets.] [+your not being there.]
               When 
               [-she] [+aunt Agatha]
               sits down to the piano
               [+the audience probably thought it was a duet.]
               She makes quite enough noise for two people."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "That is very horrid to her, and not very nice to me," answered Dorian, laughing.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Lord Henry looked at him. Yes: he was certainly wonderfully handsome,
            [-good looking,]
            with his finely-curled scarlet lips, his frank blue eyes, his crisp gold hair. There 
            was something in his face that made one trust him at once. All 
            [---]
            the candour of youth was there, as well as youth's passionate purity. One felt that he 
            had kept himself unspotted by the world. No wonder Basil Hallward worshipped him. He 
            was made to be worshipped. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "You are too charming to go in for philanthropy, Mr. Gray, far too charming," and 
               Lord Henry flung himself down on the divan, and opened his cigarette-case.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Hallward had been busy mixing his colours, and getting his brushes ready. He was 
            looking worried, and when he heard Lord Henry's last remark, he glanced at him, 
            hesitated for a moment, and then said,
            <quote>
               "Harry, I want to finish this picture today. Would you think it awfully rude of me 
               if I asked you to go away?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Lord Henry smiled, and looked at Dorian Gray.
            <quote>
               "Am I to go, Mr. Gray," he asked. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Oh, please don't, Lord Henry. I see that Basil is in one of his sulky moods, and I
               can't bear him when he sulks. Besides I want you to tell me why i should not go in 
               for philanthropy."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I don't know that I shall tell you that, Mr. Gray. But I certainly will not
               [-----]
               [+turn away now that]
               you have asked me to stop. You don't really mind, Basil? Do you? you have often told 
               me that you liked your sitters to have someone to chat to."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Hallward bit his lip.
            <quote>
               "If Dorian wishes it, of course you must stay. Dorian's whims are laws to everybody,
               except himself."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Lord Henry took up his hat and gloves.
            <quote>
               "you are very pressing, Basil, but I am afraid I must go. I have promised to meet a 
               man at the Orleans. Goodbye, Mr. Gray. Come and see me some afternoon in Curzon 
               Street. I am always at home at five o'clock."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Basil," cried Dorian Gray, "if Lord Henry goes I shall go too. You never open your
               lips while you are painting, and it is horribly dull standing on a platform, and 
               trying to look pleasant. Ask him to stay. I insist upon it."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Stay, Harry, to oblige Dorian, and to oblige me," said Hallward, gazing intently at 
               the picture. "It is quite true. I never talk when I am working
               [+and never listen, either,]
               and it must be dreadfully tedious for my unfortunate sitters. I beg you to stay."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "But what about my man at the Orleans?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Hallward laughed.
            <quote>
               "I  don't think there will be any difficulty about that. Sit down again, Harry, and 
               now Dorian, get up on the platform and don't move about too much, or pay any 
               attention to what Lord Henry says. He has got a very bad influence over all his 
               friends, with the exception of myself."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Dorian stepped up on the dais, with the air of a young 
            [---] [+Greek]
            martyr, and made a little moue of discontent to Lord Henry. After a few moments he said 
            to him,
            <quote>
               "Have you really got a very bad influence,
               [+Lord Henry,]
               as bad as Basil says?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               There is no such thing as a good influence, Mr. Gray. All influence is immoral -- 
               immoral, from the scientific point of view."
            </quote>
         </p>         
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Why?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Because to influence a person, is to give him one's own soul. He does not think his
               [-own] [+natural]
               thoughts, or burn with his 
               [-own] [+natural]
               passions. His virtues are not
               [-natural] [+real]
               to him. His sins, if there are such things as sins, are borrowed. He becomes an echo 
               of someone else's music, an actor of a part that has not been written for him. The 
               aim of life is self-development. To realize 
               [-oneself] [+one's nature]
               perfectly -- that is what each of us is here for. People are afraid of themselves, 
               now-a-days. They have forgotten the highest of all duties, the duty that one 
               [+owes to]
               oneself. Of course they are charitable. They feed the hungry, and clothe the beggar. 
               But their own souls starve, and are naked. Courage has gone out of our race. Perhaps 
               we never really had it. The terror of society, which is the basis of morals, the 
               terror of God, which is the secret of religion, -- these are the two things that 
               govern us. And yet..."
               [-I belive..."]
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Just turn your head a litte more to the right, Dorian, like a good boy," said 
               Hallward, deep in his work, and only conscious that a look had come into 
               [-Dorians] [+the lad's]
               face that he had never seen there before. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "And yet," continued Lord Henry, in his low musical voice, and with that graceful 
               wave of the hand that 
               [--- all thought] [+was]
               so characterisitic of him, and that he had even in his Eton days, "I believe that if 
               one man were to live his life out fully and completely, were to give form to every 
               feeling, expression to every thought, reality to every dream -- I believe that the 
               world would gain such a fresh impulse of youth that 
               [---]
               would forget the maladies of medievalism, and return to the 
               [-Greek] [+Hellenic] 
               ideal, to something finer, richer than the 
               [-Greek] [+Hellenic] 
               ideal, it may be. But the bravest man amongst us is afraid of himself. The 
               mutilation of the savage 
               [------------]
               has its tragic survival in the self-denial that mars our lives. We are punished for 
               [-it.] [+our refusals.]
               Every impulse that we 
               [-strangle]
               strive to strangle broods in
               [-------] [+the mind,]
               and poisons us. The body sins once, and is done with sin, for action is a mode of 
               purification. Nothing remains 
               [+then]
               but the 
               [-memory] [+recollection]
               of a pleasure, 
               [+or the luxury of a regret.]
               The only way to get rid of a temptation is to yield to it. Resist it -- and your 
               soul grows sick with longing for 
               [-what] [+the things] it has forbidden to itself, 
               with desire for what its monstrous laws have made monstrous and unlawful. It has 
               been said that the great events of the world take place in the brain. It is in the 
               brain, and the brain only, that the great sins of the world 
               [-----] [+take place also.]
               You, Mr. Gray, you yourself with your rose-red youth, and your rose-white boyhood, 
               you have 
               [+perhaps]
               had passions that have made you afriad, thoughts that have filled you with terror, 
               day-dreams and sleeping dreams whose mere memory 
               [-stains] [+might stain]
               your cheek with shame." 
               [-----"]
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Stop,"
               [-said] [+-whispered] [+murmered]
               Dorian Gray, "stop. You bewilder me. I don't know what to say. There is some answer 
               to you, but I cannot find it. Basil, I am tired standing. I 
               [-will] [+must]
               go out and sit in the garden. The air is stifling here."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "My dear fellow, I am so sorry. When I am painting, I 
               [-never] [+can't] 
               think of anything else. But you never sat better. You were perfectly still. And I 
               have caught the effect I wanted, the half-parted lips, and the bright look in the 
               eyes. I don't know what Harry has been saying to you, but he has certainly made you 
               have the most wonderful expression. I suppose he has been paying you compliments. 
               You musn't believe a word that he says."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "He has certainly not been paying me compliments. Perhaps that is the reason I don't 
               think I believe any 
               [-word that he has said."] [+thing he has told me."]
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "you know you believe it all," said Lord Henry, looking at him with his dreamy
               heavy-lidded eyes. 
               [-"Let me] [+"I will]
               come to the garden with you. We will finish our conversation there. It is horribly 
               hot in the studio. Basil, let us have something iced to drink, something with 
               strawberries in it." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Certainly, Harry. Just touch the bell, and when Parker comes I will tell him what 
               you want. I have got to touch up this background, so I will join you later on. Don't 
               keep Dorian too long. I have never been in better form for painting than I am today. 
               This is going to be my masterpiece. It is my masterpiece as it stands."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Lord Henry went out to the garden, and found Dorian Gray burying his face in the great 
            cool 
            [---]
            lilac-blossoms, feverishly drinking in their perfume as if it had been wine. He 
            [---]
            came close to him, and put his hand upon his shoulder.
            <quote>
               "You are quite right to do that," he murmured. "Nothing can cure the soul but the 
               senses, just as nothing can cure the senses but the soul."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            The lad started and drew back. He was bare-headed and the leaves had tossed his 
            rebellious curles, and tangled all their gilded threads. There was a look of fear in 
            his eyes, such as people have when they are suddenly awakened. His finely 
            [-curved] [+chiselled]
            nostrils quivered, and some hidden nerve shook the scarlet of his lips and left them 
            trembling. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Yes:" continued Lord Henry, "that is one of the great secrets of life -- to cure 
               the soul by means of the senses, and the senses by means of the soul. You are a 
               wonderful boy. You know more than you think you know, just as you know less than you 
               want to know."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Dorian Gray frowned an turned his head away. He could not help liking the tall graceful
            young man who was standing by him. His romantic olive-coloured face, and worn 
            [-weary] 
            expression, interested him. There was something in his low languid voice that 
            [+was]
            fascinating.
            [---.]
            His cool, white 
            [+flower-like]
            hands, even, had a curious charm. They moved, as he spoke, 
            [-and made a]
            like music, and seemed to have a language of their own. But he felt afraid of him, and 
            ashamed of being afraid. Why had it been left for a stranger to reveal himself to 
            himself? He had known Basil Hallward for four months, but the friendship between them 
            had never altered him. Suddenly there had come someone across his life who seemed to 
            [+have] 
            disclosed to him 
            [-a new ---.] [+life's mystery.]
            And yet what was there to be afraid of? He was not a schoolboy, or a girl. It was 
            absurd to be frightened. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Let us go and sit 
               [-on the seat,"] [+in the shade,"]
               said Lord Henry. "If you stay any longer in this glare you will be quite spoiled, 
               and Basil will never paint you again. You really must not let yourself become 
               sunburnt. It would be very unbecoming to you." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "What does it matter?" cried Dorian laughing, as he sat down on the seat that was at 
               the end of the garden.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "It should matter everything to you, Mr. Gray."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Why?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Because you have now the most marvellous youth, and youth is the one thing worth 
               having."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I don't feel that, Lord Henry."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "No: you don't feel it now. Someday, when you are old and wrinkled and ugly, when 
               thought has seared your forehead with its lines, and passion branded your lips with 
               its 
               [-terrible] [+hideous]
               fires, you will fell it,
               [+you will feel it terribly.]
               If you set yourself to know life you will look evil, if you are afraid of life you 
               will 
               [-be expressionless, and vacant, and] [+look]
               common. Now, wherever you go, you charm the world. You have a wonderfully beautiful 
               face, Mr. Gray, and Beauty 
               [-like yours]
               is 
               [+a form of]
               Genius, is higher indeed than Genius, as it needs no explanation. It is one of the 
               great facts of the world, like sunlight, or spring time, or the reflection in dark 
               waters of that silver shell we call the moon. It cannot be questioned. It has its 
               divine right of soverignty. It makes princes of those that have it. People say 
               sometimes that Beauty is only superficial. That may be so. But at least it is not so 
               superficial as thought. 
               [+Besides,]
               It is only shallow people who do not judge by appearances. The true mystery 
               [+of the world]
               is the visible, not the invisible."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Yes, Mr. Gray. The gods have been good to you. But what the gods give, they quickly 
               take away. you have only a few years really in which to live. When your youth goes, 
               your
               [---]
               beauty will go with it, and then you will suddenly discover that there are no 
               triumphs left for you, and have to content yourself with those mean triumphs that 
               the memory of your past will make worse than defeats. Every month as it passes 
               brings you nearer to something dreadful. Time is jealous of you, and wars against 
               your lilies and 
               [+your]
               roses. You will become sallow, and hollow-cheeked, and dull eyed. You will suffer,
               horribly."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Remember your youth, while you have it. Don't squander the gold of your days, 
               listening to the tedious, trying to improve the hopeless failure, or giving away 
               your life to the ignorant, the common,
               [+and]
               the vulgar, which are the aims of the false ideal of our days. Live! Live the 
               wonderful life that is in you! Let nothing be lost upon you. Be always searching for 
               new sensations. Be afraid of nothing."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "A new Hedonism! That is what our age wants. You might be its visible symbol. With 
               your personality there is nothing you could not do. The world belongs to you for a 
               season. The moment I met you, I saw that you were quite unconscious of what you 
               really are, and might be. There was so much about you that charmed me that I felt 
               I must tell you something about yourself. I thought how tragic it would be if you 
               were wasted. For, there is such a little time that your youth will last, such a 
               little time."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "The common hillflowers wither, but they blossom again. The laburnum will be as 
               golden next 
               [-year,]
               [+June,]
               as it is now. In a month there will be purple stars on the clemantis, and year after
               year the green night of its leaves will have its purple stars. But we never get back 
               our youth. The pulse of joy that beats in us at twenty, becomes sluggish. We 
               degenerate into hideous 
               [+puppets]
               haunted by the memory of the passions of which we were afraid, and the exquisite 
               temptations that we did not dare to yield to. Youth! Youth! There is nothing in the 
               world but youth!"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Dorian Gray listened, opened-eyed, and wondering. The Spray of lilac fell from his hand 
            [---] [+upon] the [-dust.] [+gravel.]
            A furry bee came and buzzed round it for a moment. Then it began to scramble all over 
            the 
            [-flower's] 
            [?fettered]
            purple of the tiny blossoms. He watched it with that strange interest in trivial 
            things, that we try to develop, when tings of high import make us afraid. after a time 
            it flew away. He saw it creeping into the stained trumpet of a Tyrian convolvulus. The 
            flower seemed to quiver, and then swayed gently to and fro.            
         </p>
         <p>
            Suddenly Hallward appeared at the door of the studio, and made frantic signs for them 
            to come in. They turned to each other, and smiled.
            <quote>
               "I am waiting," cried Hallward, "do come in. THe light is quite perfect, and you can 
               bring your drinks." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            They rose up, and sauntered down the walk together. Two green and white butterflies 
            fluttered past them, and in the pear-tree at the end of the garden a thrush began to 
            sing.
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "You are glad you have met me, 
               [-Dorian,"] [+Mr. Gray,"]
               said Lord Henry.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Yes: I am glad now. I wonder 
               [-will] [+shall]
               I always be glad."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Always! that is a dreadful word. It makes me shudder when I hear it. Women are so 
               fond of it. They spoil every romance by trying to make it last for ever. 
               [-Like guests, they terrify one with the prospect of --- eternity, --- to terrify one, I should say [+for] after all.]
               The only difference between a caprice, and a life-long passoin, is that the caprice 
               lasts a little longer."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            As they entered the studio, Dorian Gray put his hand upon Lord Henry's arm. 
            <quote>
              "In that case, let our friendship be a caprice," he murmured, 
              [+flushing [----] at his own boldness,]
              and 
              [---]
              then stepped up on the platform, and resumed
              [------------] [+his] 
              pose.
              [------------]
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Lord Henry flung himself into a large widker arm-chair, and watched him. The sweep and 
            dash of the brush on the canvas made the only sound that broke the 
            [-silence,] [+stillness,]
            except when Hallward stepped back, now and then, to look at his work from a distance. 
            In the 
            ????
            slanting beams, that streamed through the open doorway, the dust danced and was golden. 
            The heavy scent of the roses seemed to brood over everthing.
         </p>
         <p>
            After about a quarter of an hour, Hallward stopped painting, looked for a long time at 
            Dorian Gray, and then for a long time at 
            [-his]
            the 
            [-canvas,] [+picture,] 
            biting the end of one of his huge brushes, and 
            [-frowning.] [+smiling.]
            <quote>
               "It is quite finished," he cried, at last, and stooping down he wrote his name in 
               thin vermillion letters on the left hand corner of the canvas.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Lord Henry came and examined the picture. It was certainly a wonderful work of art, and 
            a wonderful likeness as well. 
            [-Most modern portrait paintings come under the head of elegant fiction, or if it aims at realism, gives one something between a caricature and a photograph. But this different. It [---] had all the mystery of life, and all the mystery of beauty. Within the world, as men know it, there is a giner world that only artists know of, -- [----] artists, or those to whom the temperament of the artist has been given. Creation within creation -- that is what Basil Hallward had arrived at, that is what he had attuned to]
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "My dear fellow, I congratulate you most warmly," 
               [+he]
               said.
               [-Lord Henry.]
               [-"Dorian,] ["Mr. Gray,]
               come look at yourself."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            The lad started, as if awakened 
            [-by] [+from]
            some dream.
            <quote>
               "Is it really finished?" he murmured, 
               [-coming] [+skipping] 
               down from the platform.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Quite finished," said Hallward, "and you have sat splendidly today. I am awfully 
               obliged to you." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "That is entirely due to me," broke in Lord Henry. "Isn't it, Mr. Gray?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Dorian 
            [-Gray]
            made no answer, but passed in front of his picture, and 
            [-looked at] [+turned towards]
            it. He drew back, and his cheeks flushed for a moment with pleasure, when he saw it. A 
            look of joy came into his eyes as if he had recognized himself for the first time. He 
            stood there motionless, and in wonder, dimly conscious that Hallward was speaking to 
            him, but not catching the meaning of his words. The sense of his own beauty came on him 
            like a new revelation. He had never felt it before. Basil Hallward's
            [-panegyric] [+compliments]
            had seemed to him to be merely the charming exaggerations of friendship. He had 
            listened to them, laughed at them, forgotten them. They had not influenced his nature. 
            Then how come Lord Henry, with 
            [-his terrible account of the horrors of old age,] [+his strange panegyric on youth, his terrible hints at its brevity,]
            that had stirred him, and the time, and now as he stood gazing at the shadow of his own 
            loveliness, the full reality of the description flashed across him. Yes: there would be 
            a day when his face would be wrinkled and wizened, his eyes dim and colourless, the 
            grace of his figure broken and deformed. The scarlet would pass away from his lips, and 
            the gold steal from his hair. The life that was to make his soul would mar his body. He 
            would become ignoble, hideous, and uncouth. As he thought of it, a sharp pang of pain 
            struck like a knife across him, and made each delicate fibre of his nature quiver. His 
            eyes deepened into amethyst, and a mist of tears came across them. He felt as if a hand 
            of ice had been laid upon his heart. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Don't you like it?" cried hallward at last, stung a little by the lad's silence, 
               and not understanding what it meant.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Of course he likes it," said Lord Henry. "Who wouldn't like it? It is one of the 
               greatest things in modern art. I will give you anything you like to ask for it. I 
               must have it."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "It is not my property, Harry."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Whose property is it?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Dorian's, of course."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "He is a very lucky fellow."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "How sad it is," murmured Dorian Gray, with his eyes still fixed upon
               [-the picture.] [+his portrait.]
               "How sad it is! I shall grow old, and horrid, and dreadful. 
               [-Life will write its lines across my face. Passion will sear it and thought twist it from its form.]
               But this picture will remain always young. It will never be older than this 
               [---] [+particular]
               day of June... If it was only the other way! If it was I who
               [-remained] [+was to be]
               always young, and the picture that 
               [+was to]
               grow old! For 
               [-that] [+this]
               -- for
               [-that,] [+this,]
               I should give everything!
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "You would not care for that
               [+arrangement,]
               Basil," cried Lord Henry, laughing. "it would be rather hard lines on you."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I should object very strongly, Harry." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Dorian Gray turned and looked at him.
            <quote>
               "I believe you would, Basil. You like your art better than you like your friends. I 
               am no more to you than 
               [-your]
               a green bronze
               [Hermes.] [+figure.]
               Hardly as much, I dare say. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Hallward stared in amazement. It was so unlike Dorian to speak like that. What had 
            happened? He seemed 
            [-quite changed, and]
            almost angry. His 
            [-was]
            face was flushed, and his cheeks 
            [-seemed]
            burning. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Yes:" he continued, "I am less to you than your ivory
               [---,] [+Hermes,]
               or your silver faun. You will like them always. How long will you like me? Till I 
               have my first wrinkle, I suppose. I know now that when one loses one's youth, one 
               loses everything. Your picture has taught me that. 
               [-Harry] [+Lord Henry]
               is perfectly right. Youth is the only thing worth having."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Hallward turned pale, and caught his hand. 
            <quote>
               "Dorian! Dorian! he cried, "don't talk like that. I have never had such a friend as 
               you, and I shall never have such another. YOu are not jealous of material things, 
               are you?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I am jealous of everything whose beauty does not die. I am jealous of the portrait 
               you have painted for me. Why should it keep what I must lose? Every moment that 
               passes takes something from me, and gives something to it." 
            </quote>
            The hot tears flushed to his eyes; 
            [-and turning he]
            he tore his hand away, and flinging himself of the divan he buried his face in 
            [-his hands]
            the cushion.
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "This is your doing, Harry," said Hallward, bitterly.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "My doing?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Yes: yours, and you know it."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Lord Henry shrugged his shoulders.
            <quote>
               "It is the real Dorian Gray, that is all," he answered.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "It is not."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Comme vous voulez, mon cher."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "You should have gone away when I asked you."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I stayed when you asked me."               
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Harry, I can't quarrel with my two best friends at once, but between you both, you 
               have made me hate the best piece of work I have ever done, and I will destroy it. 
               What is it but canvas and colour? I will not let it come across our three lives, and 
               mar them."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Dorian Gray lifted his golden head from the pillow, and looked at him with pallid face 
            and tear-stained eyes, as he walked over to the deal painting-table that was set 
            beneath the 
            [+large curtained]
            window. What was he doing there?  His
            [-hands] [+fingers]
            strayed about among the litter of tin tubes and dry brushes seeking for something. Yes: 
            it was the long palette-knife with its thin blade of lithe
            [---]
            steal. He had found it at last. He was going to rip up the canvas.
         </p>
         <p>
            With a stifled sob Dorian Gray leapt from the couch, and rushing over to Hallward tore 
            the knife out of his hand, and flung it to the end of the studio.
            <quote>
               "Don't, Basil, don't," he cried: "It would be murder!"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I am glad you appreciate my work at last, Dorian," said Hallward coldly, when he 
               had recovered from his suprise. "I never thought you would."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Appreciate it? I am in love with it, Basil. It is part of myself. I feel that."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Well, as soon as you are dry, you shall be varnished, and framed, and sent home. 
               Then you can do what you like with yourself." and he walked across the room and rang 
               the bell for tea. "You will have tea of course, Dorian? And so will you Harry. It is 
               the only simple pleasure left to us." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I don't like simple pleasures," said Lord Henry, "and I don't like scenes, 
               [+except on the stage.]
               What 
               [-silly] [+absurd] 
               fellows you are, both of you! I wonder who it was defined man as a rational animal. 
               It was the most premature definition ever given. Man is many things, but he is not 
               rational. I am glad he is not, after all; though I wish you chaps would not 
               squabble over the picture. You must better let me have it, Basil. 
               [-Dorian] [+This silly boy]
               doesn't really want it, and I do. 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "If you let any one have it but me, Basil, I will never forgive you," cried Dorian 
               Gray. And I don't allow anyone to call me a silly boy."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "You know the picture is yours, Dorian. I gave it to you before 
               [+it]
               existed." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "And you know you
               [-are] [+have been a little]
               silly, 
               [-Dorian,] [+Mr. Gray,]
               and that you don't
               [+really]
               mind being called a boy."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "There 
               [---] [+came]
               a knock
               [-at] [+to]
               the door, and the butler entered with the tea-tray and set it down upon a small 
               Japanese 
               [---.] [+table.]
               There was a rattle of cups and saucers, and the hissing of a 
               [+fluted]
               Georgian 
               [---]
               urn. Two 
               [---] [+globe-shaped] 
               China dishes were brought in by a page. Dorian Gray went over and poured the tea 
               out. The two men sauntered launguidly to the table, and examined what was 
               [-in the dishes.] [+under the covers.]
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Let us go to the theater, tonight" said Lord Henry. "There is sure to be something 
               on, somewhere. I have promised to dine at White's, but it is only with an old 
               friend, so I can send him a wire and say that I am ill, or that I am prevented from 
               coming in consequence of a subsequent engagement. I think that would be a rather 
               nice excuse.
               [+It would have the merit of candour."]
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "It is such a bore putting on one's dress-clothes," said Hallward. "And when one has 
               them on, they are so horrid."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Yes:" answered Lord Henry, dreaming. "The costume of our day is detestable. It is 
               so sombre, so depressing. Sin is the only colour-element left in modern life."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "You must really not say such things like that before Dorian, Harry."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Before which Dorian? The one who is pouring out tea for us, or the one in the 
               picture?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Before either."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I should like to come to the theater with you, Lord Henry," said 
               [-Dorian Gray.] [+the lad.]
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Then you shall come. And you will come too, Basil, won't you?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               [- The --------]
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I can't really. I would sooner not. I have a lot of work to do."
            </quote>
         </p>         
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Well, then, you and I will go alone, 
               [-Dorian."] [+Mr. Gray."]
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Very well."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Basil Hallward bit his lip, and walked over, cup in hand, to the picture.
            <quote>
               "I will stay with the real Dorian," he said smiling.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Is it the real Dorian?" cried the
               [-lad,] [+original of the portrait,]
               running across to them.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "At least it will never change," said Hallward.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "What a fuss people make about fidelity," murmured Lord Henry. "And after all, it is 
               purely a question of physiology. It has nothing to do with our own will. It is an 
               accident, or a result of temperament. Young men want to be faithful, and are not: 
               old men want to be faithless, and cannot: that is all one can say."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Don't go to the theater tonight, Dorian," said Hallward. "Stop and dine with me."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I can't, really."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Why?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Because I have promised Lord Henry to go with him."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "He won't like you better for keeping your promises. I beg you not to go." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            Dorian 
            [+Gray]
            laughed and shook his head. 
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I entreat you."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            The lad hesitated, and looked over at Lord Henry who was watching them from the 
            tea-table with an amused smile.
            <quote>
               "I must go, Basil," he answered.
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Very well," said Hallward, and he walked 
               [-back to the tea table] [+over]
               and laid his cup on the tray. "It is rather late, and, as you have to dress, you had 
               better lose no time. Goodbye, Harry; goodbye, Dorian. Come and see me soon. Come 
               tomorrow."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Certainly."
               [----]
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "You won't forget?"
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "No, of course not."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "And... Harry."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Yes: Basil."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Remember what I asked you when we were in the garden this morning." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "Don't be afraid." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I trust you." 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               "I wish I could trust myself," cried Lord Henry, laughing. "Come,
               [-Dorian,] [+Mr. Gray.]
               My hansom is outside, and I can drop you at your own place. Goodbye, Basil. It has 
               been a most interesting afternoon."
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            As the door closed behind them, 
            [-Basil]
            Hallward flung himself on a sofa, and 
            [-hid his face in his hands.] [+and a look of pain came into his face.]
         </p>
      </div>     
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
